[SPEAKER_01]: Live in Salford for the very first time in this election, it's Sunak versus Starmer, the ITV debate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the first head-to-head debate in the 2024 general election with these two men who want to run the country, Rishi Sunak and Keir Starmer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, good evening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tonight's debate is set against the toughest of backdrops.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since the UK last went to the polls, we've had a pandemic, Putin's invasion of Ukraine, and a cost-of-living crisis which is still hitting families hard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Huge geopolitical threats loom large, not least, of course, climate change.
[SPEAKER_01]: We all know how tough it's been.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't need the politicians to remind us.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what are these two men going to offer us?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who are they?
[SPEAKER_01]: And why should they earn our vote?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can they level with us when we know that finances are almost impossibly tight?
[SPEAKER_01]: Later tonight, you'll be able to see what other parties are offering when they're interviewed live on ITV1 by Anushka Astana.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the conversation will continue on the national and regional news.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, let's get on with tonight's debate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keir Starmer, your opening statement, please.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_02]: This election is all about a choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: More of the chaos and division we've seen for the last 14 years or turning the page and rebuilding with Labour.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have ambition for our country and have a practical plan to deliver it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've changed the Labour Party and put it back in the service of working people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now I'm seeking your backing to change our country, to make it work once again for you and your family.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rishi Sunak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uncertain times call for a clear plan and bold action.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'll keep this simple.
[SPEAKER_03]: In five weeks, either Keir Starmer or I will be Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_03]: Beyond raising your taxes and raiding your pensions, no-one knows what Labour would actually do.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you know what I would do?
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll cut your taxes, protect your pension, and reduce immigration.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have a clear plan for a more secure future for you and your family.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, Rishi Sunak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, we invited viewers from right across the country to submit questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have independently selected the questioners here with us this evening.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll also raise some points made by people who couldn't be here.
[SPEAKER_01]: The two leaders don't know what they'll be asked.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also here, people who'll listen to tonight's debate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some have voted Conservative and Labour in the past and think they will do so on July the 4th.
[SPEAKER_01]: And some have voted for other parties or are undecided.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can join the debate wherever you are by using the hashtag ICVdebate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just before we go to our first question, a reminder that each leader will have 45 seconds to respond initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, our first question, on the cost of living, Paula from Huddersfield.
[SPEAKER_00]: Paula.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good evening, both.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have worked since I was 15 years old and at the moment I hold a full-time stable job.
[SPEAKER_00]: My children have left home.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the last few years I've found it very difficult to make ends meet and the money simply doesn't go far enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: All I do is work to live.
[SPEAKER_00]: My food bill is nearly doubled.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm in arrears with my bills.
[SPEAKER_00]: I spend my weekends back cooking so I don't have to turn on my oven in peak times.
[SPEAKER_00]: My savings are gone and I'm genuinely worried about my future.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think you actually understand how this is for people like me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what can you do about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you very much indeed, Paula, for your question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rishi Sunak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, Paula, I know how much of a strain the last few years have put on your family finances, the family finances of everyone in our country.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why my priority has always been to do what I can to support you.
[SPEAKER_03]: That started with bold action, like the furlough scheme during the pandemic, and more recently, my clear plan to bring inflation back to normal.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now, our economy is growing again, wages are rising, and crucially, we are able to now start cutting your taxes.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I know you're only just starting to see the benefits of that, as you described.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the choice at this election is with my clear plan and bold action to keep cutting your taxes to give you financial security or put all that progress at risk with higher taxes, £2,000 worth of higher taxes under the Labour Party.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, Rishi Sunak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here's Dhan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Paul, I'm really, really sorry to hear the position that you're in.
[SPEAKER_02]: It must be really, really difficult on a daily basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there'll be millions of people watching this who feel in a similar position to you that the cost of living crisis is really bearing down on them with constant worry.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not going to pretend that
[SPEAKER_02]: Ukraine and Covid hasn't made things worse.
[SPEAKER_02]: But this government has lost control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Liz Truss crashed the economy.
[SPEAKER_02]: They made it worse here than in other countries.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's people like you that are paying the price.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if a government loses control of the economy, as they have,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's working people that pay the price.
[SPEAKER_02]: And Liz Truss's advisers are in the House of Lords.
[SPEAKER_02]: She's going to be a candidate at the next election.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rishi Sunak is putting her forward.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've got to stop this chaos, got to stop the division, turn a page and start to rebuild under Labour.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you for those opening statements, 45 seconds each.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to turn to you first, Keir Starmer, the point that Rishi Sunak made is the economy is growing again, the plan is working, is his view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, he says the plan is working.
[SPEAKER_02]: He says the plan is working.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the question for him is, why has he called the election now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if he thinks things are going to get better towards the second half of this year, why has he called it now?
[SPEAKER_02]: He's called it now because he knows, and I'll ask him this, he knows inflation is going to go back up.
[SPEAKER_02]: He knows energy prices are going to go back up in the autumn.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what he's not telling you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So he says the plan is working, but I don't think he believes the plan is working, because if he thought the plan is working, he wouldn't have called this election right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Rishi Sunak?
[SPEAKER_03]: I think it's slightly ironic, because from the moment I got this job, Keir Starmer was telling me, call an election, call an election.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now that we've called an election, he's saying, oh, no, don't have an election, because I don't want to tell you what I'm going to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is the choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: for everybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: The plan is working, of course, I know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everyone is only just starting to feel the benefits of it, but inflation is back to normal, wages are growing, taxes are now being cut.
[SPEAKER_03]: Keir Starmer would put all that progress at risk.
[SPEAKER_03]: He would put up everyone's taxes by £2,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: £2,000 in higher taxes for every working family in our country after all the hard work and sacrifice we've been through.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not the right course of action.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know why you want to put up people's taxes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Paul, I just don't know how you feel when you hear a Prime Minister say, having heard what you're going through, that the plan is working, it's all all right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I meet so many people who are struggling with their bills and the Prime Minister just keeps saying, he lives in a different world, that it's all all right.
[SPEAKER_03]: If people are struggling with their bills, why do you want to make it harder for them by saddling them with £2,000 worth of higher taxes?
[SPEAKER_03]: How is that going to make Paula or anyone's life easier?
[SPEAKER_03]: Could you respond directly to Rishi Sunak?
[SPEAKER_02]: This is the Prime Minister who's been part of a government that has put up tax 26 times.
[SPEAKER_02]: The last manifesto that they had in 2019 said, we won't put up national insurance.
[SPEAKER_02]: This man then put up national insurance.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's the British expert on tax rises.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're at the highest level for 70 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he's got the gall to say other people are going to... And are we going to hear a lot about the past?
[SPEAKER_03]: in this election but this election is about the future.
[SPEAKER_03]: This election is about the future and I'm clear that I'm going to keep cutting people's taxes as we now are.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want to put everyone's taxes up by £2,000 and this is really important.
[SPEAKER_03]: Independent Treasury officials have costed Labour's policies and they amount to a £2,000 tax rise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mark my words, Labour will raise your taxes, it's in their DNA, your work, your car, your pension, you name it, Labour will tax it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just going to just draw breath there a moment please gentlemen, we're going to be talking about tax again later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just want to bring this part of the debate back very firmly to Paula's question.
[SPEAKER_01]: She made it very clear how hard her life is at the moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: You did acknowledge it, both of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: She spends her weekends batch cooking so she doesn't have to turn her oven on during peak times.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is worry here, right before our eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: that were being echoed across the country.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the key points that Paula says is, she says, I don't think you understand how hard it is for people like me.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you going to do about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you actually connect with Paula?
[SPEAKER_01]: Rishi Sunak.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I'd ask everyone to judge me by my actions.
[SPEAKER_03]: You saw what I did during the pandemic.
[SPEAKER_03]: When disaster struck our country, I implemented the furlough scheme because I knew the devastating impact it would have on people.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you know what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Every week when I'm out and about, someone comes up to me and tells me how furlough saved their family, saved their home, because that's who I am.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I don't want to put that progress at risk.
[SPEAKER_03]: I want to keep delivering financial security by cutting people's taxes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas the Labour Party want to keep putting people's taxes up and that's not going to help anyone overcome the challenges they're facing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Paula wants to know what you're going to do about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think what you put to the Prime Minister is how does he connect?
[SPEAKER_02]: Paula, what I would say is this.
[SPEAKER_02]: My dad worked in a factory.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was a toolmaker.
[SPEAKER_02]: My mum was a nurse.
[SPEAKER_02]: We didn't have a lot of money when I was growing up.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we were in a position on occasion where we couldn't pay our bills.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I know how that feels.
[SPEAKER_02]: In our particular case, we had our phone cut off because we didn't have the money.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I do know the anguish of worrying when the postman comes with a bill, what is that bill going to be?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I pay for it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you saying that Rishi...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think the Prime Minister quite understands the position that you and other people are in.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do want to, if I may, just answer... No, let Richie say... No, please let Richie respond to that, please.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because this election is about the future and making people's lives better.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, I've got a clear plan to ease those anxieties that Paula and everyone is facing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because things are tough, I want to make them easier by continuing to cut your taxes.
[SPEAKER_03]: The difference of this election is Keir Starmer is going to put your taxes up by £2,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: So if people are worried about their electricity bill, their food bill, taking their kids on a holiday, £2,000 worth of tax rises are not going to help with any of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll ask again, why do you want to put everyone's taxes up?