[SPEAKER_18]: Tonight, David Cameron, Ed Miliband and Nick Clegg face our audience here in Leeds Town Hall.
[SPEAKER_18]: This is Question Time.
[SPEAKER_18]: APPLAUSE
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_18]: Over the next 90 minutes, the three party leaders are going to take the stage here and be questioned by our audience, of course, as ever.
[SPEAKER_18]: An audience that tonight is made up of three lots of 25% who intend to vote for each of those three party leaders, and the remaining 25% who are either undecided or supporting other parties.
[SPEAKER_18]: Now, during this programme,
[SPEAKER_18]: As ever on Question Time, you can of course text or tweet.
[SPEAKER_18]: Our hashtag is BBC QT.
[SPEAKER_18]: You can follow us at BBC Question Time.
[SPEAKER_18]: You can text comments to 83981.
[SPEAKER_18]: You can push that old red button and see what other people are saying.
[SPEAKER_18]: But let's now get cracking and hear from the leader of the Conservative Party, David Cameron.
[SPEAKER_18]: Our first question comes from Jenny Johnson, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Jenny Johnson.
[SPEAKER_24]: Were you put to bed with rumours that you plan to cut child tax credit and restrict child benefits to children?
[SPEAKER_19]: Well thank you Jenny for that question.
[SPEAKER_19]: No, I don't want to do that.
[SPEAKER_19]: This report that was out today is something I rejected at the time as Prime Minister and I reject it again today.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I do think it's important we go on reforming welfare.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's worth remembering when I became Prime Minister we had a situation where some families were getting £70,000, £80,000, even £90,000 of housing benefit for one house.
[SPEAKER_19]: And think how many people watching this programme were going out, working hard, paying taxes to keep that family in that house.
[SPEAKER_19]: A house they could never afford to live in.
[SPEAKER_19]: So we've got to go on reforming welfare.
[SPEAKER_19]: Let's make sure that work always pays.
[SPEAKER_19]: And let's go on doing what we've done for the last five years, which is get two million more people back into work.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the most important thing we can do, helping people off welfare into work.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the sort of country I want to build the next five years.
[SPEAKER_18]: Sorry, you said you didn't want to put to bed the rumours that you were going to cut child tax credits, you meant you did want to put to bed the rumours?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes, we have increased child tax credits actually, we increased them by £452 under this government because I was determined that while we had to take difficult decisions, and we have, we were left an absolute nightmare situation to clear up, I wanted to make sure that child poverty continued to fall and it has fallen under this government because of what we did
[SPEAKER_18]: And so that's a guarantee that you won't.
[SPEAKER_18]: Does anybody want to come in on this?
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes, you sir, up there at the back.
[SPEAKER_18]: In the middle there.
[SPEAKER_07]: You're quoting £70,000 to £80,000 of benefits.
[SPEAKER_07]: How many families are actually claiming that amount of money?
[SPEAKER_19]: Well, it wasn't a huge number, but the fact is everyone that was, was being paid for by dozens of people going out to work, paying their taxes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Look, if you believe, as I do, we should go on reforming welfare, making sure that work always pays, helping people back into work, and keeping working people's taxes down, that's my programme.
[SPEAKER_19]: If you want unlimited welfare, more increases in welfare and higher taxes for working people, that's Ed Miliband's programme, vote for him.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I say keep reforming welfare, it's the right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_30]: You sir.
[SPEAKER_30]: I'm sorry but I just think you're either deceiving the British public or you know exactly what you're going to do but you're refusing to give specifics.
[SPEAKER_19]: and I find that very, very difficult to understand.
[SPEAKER_19]: And how can I possibly vote for you on that basis?
[SPEAKER_19]: Well, let me answer that very directly.
[SPEAKER_19]: In the last Parliament, we saved £20 billion on welfare, and we need to save something like half that in this Parliament.
[SPEAKER_19]: And as I say, if we don't save the money on welfare, and other parties don't seem to want to do that,
[SPEAKER_19]: then they're going to have to make deep cuts in things like the National Health Service, and I don't want to do that.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm going to increase spending on the National Health Service every year in the next Parliament, just as I did in the last Parliament.
[SPEAKER_19]: But we can reduce welfare.
[SPEAKER_19]: If, for instance, we get another 2 million people back to work, that will cut the welfare bills.
[SPEAKER_19]: Here's another tough choice I think we do need to make.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think we should say to young people in our country
[SPEAKER_19]: The idea that you can leave school and immediately sign on to Jobseekers Allowance, immediately get a flat with housing benefit, I don't think that should be an option anymore.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think what we should do is say to young people, we want you to have a great future.
[SPEAKER_19]: You should be earning or learning.
[SPEAKER_19]: So we'll make available the apprenticeships, make available the university places, make available the training places, but say you can't start your life on benefits.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's not the way we should work in Britain today.
[SPEAKER_25]: That's all very well, but what about those 18 to 21 year olds who don't have a support network, for them who don't have a family to turn to?
[SPEAKER_25]: Isn't that policy for them specifically going to result in more homeless young people on the streets?
[SPEAKER_19]: I think the lady makes a very important point.
[SPEAKER_19]: Anyone who clearly can't stay at home, who has to live independently because of abuse or what have you, we have to make special provision for them and we would.
[SPEAKER_19]: But the situation today, where you can, age 18, leave school, sign on, get a flat, rather than work,
[SPEAKER_19]: or earn and learn at the same time.
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't think that's right.
[SPEAKER_19]: Look, other countries in Europe have almost abolished youth unemployment because they've taken this approach in, say, Germany or in Holland.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think we should do the same thing.
[SPEAKER_19]: Look, we have created two million jobs in the last five years.
[SPEAKER_19]: Youth unemployment has come plummeting down.
[SPEAKER_19]: If we stick to the economic plan that's working, we can continue to get unemployment down and give young people what I want, which is the opportunity of an apprenticeship or a university place
[SPEAKER_19]: and the chance of a great career.
[SPEAKER_19]: Starting a life on benefits, frankly, is no life at all.
[SPEAKER_18]: David Cameron, can you just come back to the question that the man here asked, that either you don't know what you're going to do, you've specified getting people back to work, or you do know and you're hiding it.
[SPEAKER_18]: You know Dally Alexander today said you'd asked two years ago for a thing which included massive cuts in child benefit.
[SPEAKER_19]: No, these were some proposals that were produced that I rejected then, not least because...
[SPEAKER_19]: But you asked for them.
[SPEAKER_19]: No, I didn't ask for them.
[SPEAKER_19]: They were proposals that were... Where did they come from?
[SPEAKER_19]: In government, people produced... Look, you've got to remember, step back a second, what we inherited.
[SPEAKER_19]: I became Prime Minister at a time when there was no money left.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I bring this with me everywhere, the note that the Treasury Minister left, and it's...
[SPEAKER_19]: There it is.
[SPEAKER_19]: Dear Chief Secretary, I'm afraid there is no money.
[SPEAKER_19]: That is the situation I inherited.
[SPEAKER_19]: So we have had to make difficult decisions.
[SPEAKER_19]: over these last five years and I accept not every one of the decision has been easy for people but the truth is five years on the deficit is halved, two million people are back in work, the economy is growing faster than any major economy in the Western world and I think what this election is about
[SPEAKER_19]: is do we build on that foundation and build a really strong country where you can get a job, you can keep more of your own money to spend as you choose, you get that apprenticeship, we can build houses for people to buy and own, or do we go right back to the start with Ed Miliband potentially propped up by the SNP who want even more borrowing, even more spending, even more debt, all the things that landed us in that mess in the first place.
[SPEAKER_19]: I never want us to go back there again.
[SPEAKER_18]: Clearly there are some people who are worried that you have a plan to cut child credit and tax credits.
[SPEAKER_18]: Are you saying absolutely as a guarantee that you'll never happen?
[SPEAKER_19]: First of all, child tax credit we increased by £450.
[SPEAKER_19]: And it's not going to fall?
[SPEAKER_19]: Not going to fall.
[SPEAKER_19]: Child benefit?
[SPEAKER_19]: to me is one of the most important benefits there is.
[SPEAKER_19]: It goes directly to the family, normally to the mother.
[SPEAKER_19]: £20 for the first child, £14 for the second.
[SPEAKER_19]: It is the key part of families' budgets in this country.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now that's not what we need to change.
[SPEAKER_19]: What we need to change is, again, what did I inherit?
[SPEAKER_19]: A system
[SPEAKER_19]: where if you worked an extra hour or an extra shift, you could sometimes find you actually lost money from that extra hour or that extra shift.
[SPEAKER_19]: So universal credit that we're introducing, coming in now, means every hour you work, you keep more of the money that you earn.
[SPEAKER_19]: And we're going to introduce that right across the country.
[SPEAKER_19]: That will save money and form part of the welfare savings we need to make.
[SPEAKER_18]: Let me bring a couple more people in.
[SPEAKER_18]: The woman there, and then I'll come to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If things are so fantastic and we've all got more money to spend, why are more families relying on food banks and why are more people and more children in poverty than ever before?
[SPEAKER_19]: I think you ask an absolutely key question.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm not saying everything is perfect.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm saying we have not finished the work.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's why I'm so keen to do another five years of continuing to get the country back to work, to build a strong economy, to pay down our debts, and to hand on a really good country to our children.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's what this is all about.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm not saying we fixed it.
[SPEAKER_19]: It takes a long time to fix the mess that I was left to clear up.
[SPEAKER_19]: But what I would say is we're halfway through a building job.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now, you can keep the team that are building the strong economy or you can go back to the team, frankly, the ones that designed the building that fell down in the first place.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think that would be a terrible mistake.
[SPEAKER_18]: You want to come in and I'll come to you and then we'll go on.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_43]: You talk about the sort of country we want to hand on to our children.
[SPEAKER_43]: I don't want to hand on a country to my child where there are a million use in food banks, where people have been hit by really punitive benefit sanctions.
[SPEAKER_43]: People have died, you know, from the bedroom tax.
[SPEAKER_43]: We've got cases where people have a disabled... A woman has had a disabled daughter die and then receive a demand for bedroom tax for the spare room that disabled daughter has left behind.
[SPEAKER_43]: That is not a country I want to hand on to my child.
[SPEAKER_19]: First of all, let me say, I don't want anyone to have to rely on a food bank in our country.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's important that they're there, but I don't want anyone to have to rely on them.
[SPEAKER_19]: The most important thing we can do is to get more people into work.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the best route out of poverty.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now, two million more jobs is more than the rest of Europe put together.
[SPEAKER_19]: But have we finished the job?
[SPEAKER_19]: Someone said zero-hours contract.
[SPEAKER_19]: One in 50 jobs is a zero-hours contract.
[SPEAKER_19]: Two-thirds of the jobs we've created are full-time jobs.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now, if you're saying the job isn't finished, I absolutely agree, and that is why I'm so passionate about completing the job.
[SPEAKER_19]: And, madam, you asked, what country do you want to pass on to our children?
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't want us to go on borrowing year after year, racking up debts that we then ask our children to pay because we didn't have the courage to pay them off ourselves.
[SPEAKER_19]: And this goes to the heart of the election campaign because Ed Miliband will stand here in a few minutes time.
[SPEAKER_19]: He is saying go on with the budget deficit forever.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm saying once the economy starts to grow you should be putting money aside for a rainy day.
[SPEAKER_19]: Otherwise we will burden our children with too much debt and that's not right.
[SPEAKER_19]: What was that?
[SPEAKER_09]: Why don't you debate with him directly instead of pointing fingers at him?
[SPEAKER_19]: We debate in the House of Commons 146 times.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I would have voted for you.
[SPEAKER_19]: We debate 146 times in the House of Commons.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's not always that instructive.
[SPEAKER_19]: Actually, I think this is giving you the chance to ask questions directly.
[SPEAKER_19]: I actually think this is more powerful than a television debate.
[SPEAKER_18]: And let's go on to another question.
[SPEAKER_18]: It's a similar subject, really.
[SPEAKER_18]: Lorna Jasper, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Lorna Jasper.
[SPEAKER_39]: OK. Is needing a law to guarantee your no tax rises promise an acknowledgement that you were in the habit of lying in your pre-election promises?
[SPEAKER_18]: This, of course, is the announcement yesterday that you're going to pass the law.
[SPEAKER_19]: The reason for making this pledge is I really want to be clear with people.
[SPEAKER_19]: Over the last five years, we've made difficult decisions.
[SPEAKER_19]: We've talked about some of that tonight.
[SPEAKER_19]: It hasn't been easy, I know, for many people in Britain.
[SPEAKER_19]: But it's, I think, been the right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_19]: I now know what is in the books.
[SPEAKER_19]: I know what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I know we can finish the job without putting up people's taxes.
[SPEAKER_19]: And my fear is this.
[SPEAKER_19]: Those people
[SPEAKER_19]: who've opposed every step that we've taken, every cut we've had to make, I think they will make a cut of their own, which is to put up taxes to reach into your pay packet and to cut your pay.
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't want to do that.
[SPEAKER_19]: So if you want a government that finds more efficiencies in government spending, that goes on reforming welfare and doesn't put up taxes for working people, indeed cuts taxes for working people, that's me.
[SPEAKER_19]: If you want a government that goes on with unreformed welfare, that doesn't find savings in government spending and puts up taxes, that's the other guy.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the choice.
[SPEAKER_18]: But why do you need a law?
[SPEAKER_18]: Exactly, the question is why do you need a law?
[SPEAKER_18]: And I would cite to you what your Chancellor said.
[SPEAKER_19]: I want to put it absolutely beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_19]: I really want hard-working people in our country who work every hour, who want to have a better future for themselves and their families.
[SPEAKER_19]: I want them to know that we're not going to put up VAT or national insurance or income tax because we know we can make the remaining savings without having to attack their wallets.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the pledge I make.
[SPEAKER_18]: When Alistair Darling tried the same thing, your Chancellor said no other Chancellor in the long history of the office has felt the need to pass a law in order to convince people he has the political will to implement his own budget.
[SPEAKER_18]: Why do you suddenly need to pass a law?
[SPEAKER_19]: Because that was at a
[SPEAKER_18]: Which can be changed anyways, we know.
[SPEAKER_19]: Because that was at a time when the budget deficit was forecast to be bigger than the deficit in Greece.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's what we inherited.
[SPEAKER_19]: So making that sort of promise then was meaningless.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now, having spent five years as Prime Minister, knowing what needs to be done, and let me be clear about...
[SPEAKER_19]: what still needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_19]: We've got to save one out of every £100 the government spends for each of the next two years.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the extent of the efficiencies that are needed.
[SPEAKER_19]: And then we can start to see public spending growing again to make sure that we go on putting money into our schools and hospitals and all the important public services that we have.
[SPEAKER_19]: We may come back.
[SPEAKER_18]: Laura Jasper, do you want to come back on this question?
[SPEAKER_39]: I more or less was going to say what you said.
[SPEAKER_18]: Oh right, OK.
[SPEAKER_18]: The woman there.
[SPEAKER_18]: I don't want to have you repeating things.
[SPEAKER_22]: You say that you know what needs to be done, so why aren't you announcing where those benefits cuts are coming from?
[SPEAKER_19]: What we're saying, very precisely, is that we need to make another £30 billion of savings.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the one in £100.
[SPEAKER_19]: So £5 billion of that should come from the tax evaders and the aggressive tax avoiders.
[SPEAKER_19]: We've gone after them every year in government.
[SPEAKER_19]: We'll continue to do that.
[SPEAKER_19]: We then need to go on making savings in government departments through efficiencies, and then the welfare savings that I've talked about.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's my plan, and that gets us to a budget surplus.
[SPEAKER_19]: It means we're paying down the debts, we're passing on a better country to our children, and crucially, we're not putting up taxes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Indeed, I want to cut people's taxes.
[SPEAKER_19]: People talk about the cost of living.
[SPEAKER_19]: The biggest element of the cost of living is the tax you pay at the end of the month.
[SPEAKER_19]: and I say you should be able to earn £12,500 a year before you start paying income tax.
[SPEAKER_19]: That would take people on minimum wage working 30 hours a week out of tax altogether.
[SPEAKER_19]: We should stop taxing poor people in this country in the way that we do today and that's part of our programme for the future.
[SPEAKER_21]: But that wasn't my question, Mr Cameron.
[SPEAKER_18]: Alright, let's have another question from Chair Dear Hoolikin, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Chair Dear Hoolikin.
[SPEAKER_28]: Why do you think voters don't trust your party with our NHS?
[SPEAKER_18]: It's another question on trust, David Cameron.
[SPEAKER_18]: Why do you think voters don't trust your party with the NHS?
[SPEAKER_19]: All I can say is what I think and what I believe.
[SPEAKER_19]: And when my disabled son was desperately ill, I went to the NHS night after night.
[SPEAKER_19]: I went to different hospitals.
[SPEAKER_19]: I was in different places.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I got the most fantastic care, support, and I'd say love
[SPEAKER_19]: from those people in the NHS for my family and for my son.
[SPEAKER_19]: It was always there for me and I will always make sure it is there for other families in our country.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now, I showed you that note about we had no money when we became the government.
[SPEAKER_19]: When we got that note, we still made a very big decision, which is we said, yes, we're going to have to make cuts
[SPEAKER_19]: in some areas of government spending, but the NHS is going to get more money every year I'm Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_19]: And it has had more money, and that's why there are, compared with when I became Prime Minister, 9,000 more doctors, there are 7,000 more nurses, we're carrying out millions more operations every year.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do I think it's perfect?
[SPEAKER_19]: No I don't, and I've got a big ambition.
[SPEAKER_19]: for the next five years, which is to deliver a seven-day-a-week NHS, including seven-day opening, eight in the morning, eight in the evening, for GP surgeries.
[SPEAKER_19]: I know we can do that, because we're already delivering it to about eight million people in our country.
[SPEAKER_19]: If you elect me as Prime Minister, I'll finish the job and make sure we have seven-day opening for GP surgeries right across our country.
[SPEAKER_19]: That will really help working people to access the NHS that we all want.
[SPEAKER_18]: Why spend three billion or so on what was described as damaging and distracting reorganisations of the NHS by the King's Fund?
[SPEAKER_19]: The changes we've made actually are saving money in the NHS and because we got rid of 20,000 administrators and bureaucrats in the NHS, that's one of the ways we've been able to fund the extra doctors and the extra nurses.
[SPEAKER_19]: Again,
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't want to hark on about what I inherited, but when I became Prime Minister, the growth in the number of bureaucrats was going up four times as fast as the number of nurses.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I make the point because it's been a recovery job.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_19]: And the NHS is stronger today than it was five years ago.
[SPEAKER_34]: Good evening Mr Cameron.
[SPEAKER_34]: The fact that Jeremy Hunt has promised an extra £8 billion for the health service is very welcome, but surely anybody with half a brain can see that the NHS isn't sustainable in its present form, just pouring more and more money into it.
[SPEAKER_34]: What are your thoughts on that?
[SPEAKER_18]: How do you mean?
[SPEAKER_18]: That it needs more money?
[SPEAKER_34]: Well you can't just keep pouring more and more money.
[SPEAKER_34]: We already put a sixth of GDP into the health service, don't we?
[SPEAKER_34]: You can't keep putting more and more money into it.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's very dangerous in elections to disagree with people.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I don't agree with you, sir.
[SPEAKER_19]: I actually think... Well, you're wrong.
[SPEAKER_19]: Well, OK.
[SPEAKER_19]: I should be there.
[SPEAKER_19]: APPLAUSE
[SPEAKER_19]: I think actually if you look at our health system and compare it with others in the world it comes out very strongly on its performance and it also comes out very strongly on how cost effective it is and as we become a wealthier country we should put more money into our NHS so it's always there for us.
[SPEAKER_19]: Look there's a lot we can do
[SPEAKER_19]: to take pressure off the NHS, we've got to do better in terms of public health, we've got to do better in terms of health education, there are all sorts of things about diabetes and smoking and other things where public health issues can really take the pressure off the NHS, but I'm a profound believer that our model is the right one and if as long as I'm Prime Minister it will be free at the point of use, available to all on the basis of need and we will go on putting the money it needs into it, not least because we have taken the difficult decisions elsewhere that
[SPEAKER_19]: some people have been talking back to me.
[SPEAKER_19]: The lady behind me here.
[SPEAKER_36]: Good evening Mr Cameron.
[SPEAKER_36]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_36]: I'd just like to ask, is it really so difficult to achieve the accident emergency waiting times?
[SPEAKER_36]: Have we found a best way?
[SPEAKER_36]: And what are the actual blockers?
[SPEAKER_36]: Because it just seems that, you know, every week in the media that, you know, we're not hitting these four hour targets, so what are your plans moving forward?
[SPEAKER_19]: I think you make a really good point.
[SPEAKER_19]: Actually that local hospital here does meet the target of seeing 95% of people within four hours and it's important to have that target because we want to know that we're getting the best out of our NHS.
[SPEAKER_19]: The problem we've had recently is just the numbers of frail elderly in our country and the growth of the population of our country has put a lot of pressure on the NHS.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think my solution of having this seven-day opening for GPs and making sure GP surgeries are easier to access for people, I think that will take pressure off the NHS.
[SPEAKER_19]: I also think making sure social care works together better with the NHS, so we combine the budgets and make sure we help to get elderly people out of hospital, often blocked in beds when they could be looked after at home.
[SPEAKER_19]: Those things, I think, will keep the pressure off.
[SPEAKER_19]: But it's always going to be hard work to make sure we deliver these
[SPEAKER_18]: Just before we leave it, do you have an answer to the question, which is why don't people trust the Conservatives on the NHS?
[SPEAKER_18]: All the polling shows that.
[SPEAKER_19]: I mean, to me, it is my life's work.
[SPEAKER_19]: I profoundly believe that the NHS grows with a Conservative government like what I've been leading.
[SPEAKER_19]: We put the money in.
[SPEAKER_19]: I care about it passionately.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I've got seven days left to prove to people that the NHS, to get... Also, I'd make this point.
[SPEAKER_19]: You only ultimately have a strong NHS if you have a strong economy.
[SPEAKER_19]: We've got that strong economy now, don't put that at risk.
[SPEAKER_19]: You know where they cut the NHS?
[SPEAKER_19]: Portugal, terrible economy, cut the NHS 17%.
[SPEAKER_19]: Greece, catastrophic economy, cut the NHS 13%.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's the economies that tank and bomb where you can't support the health service that our country needs and I think we all deserve.
[SPEAKER_18]: Alright, let's go on.
[SPEAKER_18]: Bob Wilson, a question from Bob Wilson.
[SPEAKER_18]: Sorry to those of you who have your hands up.
[SPEAKER_18]: I can't bring everybody in, obviously.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, Mr Cameron.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'd like to ask, if we remain in the EU, how will you and how can you control immigration?
[SPEAKER_19]: Right.
[SPEAKER_19]: Very important question, Bob.
[SPEAKER_19]: We can control immigration from outside the EU in the way we do now by closing down these bogus colleges, and we've closed down about 800 of them, and we can do it by having a cap on migration for economic reasons coming into the country.
[SPEAKER_19]: What can you get that done?
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm going to do it inside the EU.
[SPEAKER_19]: The key changes that I'm going to make, if you re-elect me, are these.
[SPEAKER_19]: First of all, anyone coming from an EU country cannot claim unemployment benefit while they're looking for a job.
[SPEAKER_19]: Second, if they're here after six months and haven't got a job, they have to go home.
[SPEAKER_19]: Third, you'd have to work here for four years paying into the system before you get tax credits and other benefits out of the system.
[SPEAKER_19]: And fourth, if you're living here but your family's back at home, you will no longer be able to send the child benefit home to your family.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now, those four changes are big changes.
[SPEAKER_19]: They'll make a real difference and help us to control immigration.
[SPEAKER_19]: And if I'm prime minister, that's what you'll get.
[SPEAKER_18]: I'm sure a lot of people have questions on this, but a couple of points.
[SPEAKER_18]: First of all, we looked at the figures of this.
[SPEAKER_18]: Under 6% of EU nationals living in this country claim benefits of any kind.
[SPEAKER_18]: Under 6%.
[SPEAKER_18]: stopping that is going to hugely reduce the number.
[SPEAKER_18]: And the other thing is... Let me answer that one because that's important.
[SPEAKER_19]: The point I'm saying is it's the in-work benefits.
[SPEAKER_19]: At the moment, someone coming from an EU country is effectively getting around £8,000 to come and work here.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now I'm not saying they shouldn't be able to come and work here.
[SPEAKER_19]: British people can go and work in other European countries.
[SPEAKER_19]: But we do have a benefit system that skews it in favour of people coming to work here.
[SPEAKER_19]: That needs to change.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now that needs change in Europe and so you need a Prime Minister that's prepared to get change
[SPEAKER_19]: in Europe.
[SPEAKER_19]: We may come to Europe.
[SPEAKER_18]: I hope we do.
[SPEAKER_18]: One other thing.
[SPEAKER_18]: How much do you want to get the net migration from outside the EU down to?
[SPEAKER_19]: The combined figure, I want to see net immigration into the EU come down under 100,000.
[SPEAKER_19]: The reason I set that target
[SPEAKER_19]: It's back in the 1990s, we were members of the EU, we had an open and successful economy, but before Labour got in and opened the doors, we did have net migration in the tens of thousands, not the hundreds of thousands, so I believe that's the right ambition.
[SPEAKER_44]: You made similar promises in 2010.
[SPEAKER_44]: You lied.
[SPEAKER_44]: Immigration rules.
[SPEAKER_44]: How can we believe you now?
[SPEAKER_19]: Well let me answer that very directly.
[SPEAKER_19]: I made the promise and outside the EU we did get immigration down.
[SPEAKER_19]: Inside the EU, partly because the rest of the EU's economy has not performed and we've created more jobs than the rest of the EU put together, it's been very difficult to meet that target.
[SPEAKER_19]: I now need to make these benefit changes, these welfare changes, the things I've just described, and I need to negotiate those in Europe.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now I would argue I've got a track record of that.
[SPEAKER_19]: I cut the European budget, first Prime Minister ever to do it.
[SPEAKER_19]: I vetoed a European treaty because it wasn't in our national interest.
[SPEAKER_19]: I've
[SPEAKER_19]: kept Britain out of the Euro.
[SPEAKER_19]: I can deliver these things in Europe, but I need your mandate, sir, in seven days' time to get out there and win a good deal for Britain that controls immigration and gets us a better position in Europe and with me.
[SPEAKER_19]: You'll get that in-out referendum, you the British people deciding, before the end of 2017.
[SPEAKER_41]: Good evening Mr Cameron.
[SPEAKER_41]: I work in housing and I deal a lot with the homeless that live in Bradford.
[SPEAKER_41]: A lot of those come from Eastern European countries who are not able to access those types of benefits that we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_41]: What can the community do in relation to dealing with that because it does cause problems with relation to crime and drug substance misuse.
[SPEAKER_19]: Well I think we need to go back to a system, much more, where of course you are free to travel around Europe to work in a different European country.
[SPEAKER_19]: But you're not free simply to travel around Europe in order to claim benefits.
[SPEAKER_19]: Freedom of movement was always meant to be about the freedom to go and take a job.
[SPEAKER_19]: It was not freedom to go and claim benefits.
[SPEAKER_19]: So those rules need to be tougher.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's not what our benefits system is there for.
[SPEAKER_32]: Yes, Mr Cameron, all of these questions you're being asked have a moral dimension and you keep answering them in terms of economics.
[SPEAKER_32]: I'd like you to engage a little bit more with the moral dimension that these questions are asking.
[SPEAKER_19]: To me, helping someone to get a job has a moral dimension.
[SPEAKER_19]: It gives them the dignity and pride that comes with work.
[SPEAKER_19]: Helping someone to get an apprenticeship, that has a moral dimension.
[SPEAKER_19]: It gives someone the chance of a career and success.
[SPEAKER_19]: Building a house that a young family can afford to buy and own, that's got a moral dimension because it gives them a stake in the country they live in.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's the country I want to build.
[SPEAKER_19]: These plans I've got for the next five years are about taking this economic foundation that we've built these last five years, all the shared sacrifice that we've been through, but not putting that to waste, but saying let's now turn that into jobs, into pay, into houses, into good school places.
[SPEAKER_19]: And yes, also, into that sense at the end of your life that this is a country where if you work hard, you save and you do the right thing, you should get that dignity and security in retirement that I think is the right of everyone who lives in our country.
[SPEAKER_46]: If you're in a situation where you have to team up with another party, what policies would you be willing to compromise?
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm going to disappoint you because look we've got seven days to go and I'm going to fight everything I've got those next seven days to get an overall majority and the reason why I think that's right is look I think a strong decisive a more accountable government
[SPEAKER_19]: where you're not trading away, that's the trouble with coalition.
[SPEAKER_19]: You've got a great manifesto, you don't quite win the election, you go into some dark room with Nick Clegg or someone else and you start giving away some of the things that were in your programme.
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't want to do that.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think I've got a great programme about building these houses, creating these jobs, funding these apprenticeships, helping people with pensions.
[SPEAKER_19]: And crucially, this European referendum, which I've said absolutely that is a red line, I don't want to give any of these things away.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I'm going to spend the next seven days flat out for victory, and if enough people watching this programme are back at home, back me, we can have that victory and have the whole of the manifesto rather than have it bartered away in a darkened room.
[SPEAKER_18]: But you talk about a darkened room.
[SPEAKER_18]: What you said five years ago, we must sort things out as quickly as possible for the good of the country.
[SPEAKER_18]: So I want to make a big, open, comprehensive offer to the Liberal Democrats.
[SPEAKER_18]: Now it's getting closeted in a dark room with Nick Clegg.
[SPEAKER_18]: That's what's happened.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think it's completely consistent.
[SPEAKER_19]: What I'm saying is that the last election wasn't decisive.
[SPEAKER_19]: I believe I did the right thing by forming a coalition and having a decisive government to deal with the mess that we left.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I'm saying this time I think we can go one better.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I'm saying let's have a decisive outcome and these things don't have to be compromised on and we can have a really decisive government, more accountable government for you as a citizen.
[SPEAKER_44]: Winning by a mile is a good hope, but say you don't, then what if you have to be in a coalition with somebody else?
[SPEAKER_19]: Let me give one specific example of something I've been very clear about.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think the British people really do deserve a referendum on whether to stay in a reformed European Union or leave.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I've been very clear that I will not lead a government
[SPEAKER_19]: that does not deliver that pledge.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I couldn't be clearer about that red line.
[SPEAKER_19]: Because I think people, frankly, have been let down too many times about this issue.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I want everyone holding that stubby pencil in their hands in the voting booth in a week's time to know, if you get me as Prime Minister, you get that chance to have that in or out referendum.
[SPEAKER_18]: So if you couldn't govern without the Liberal Democrats on those grounds, you wouldn't govern with them either?
[SPEAKER_19]: Because they're not in favour of that.
[SPEAKER_19]: You've correctly interpreted what I've said.
[SPEAKER_19]: So what happens to the government of the country?
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm saying, if I'm to form a government, and I hope to win the election in seven days' time, we're 23 seats short of an overall majority, and so I hope to govern the country as a majority, but if I don't, for whatever reason, I've been very clear, I would not lead a government that did not contain that pledge.
[SPEAKER_19]: Couldn't be clearer.
[SPEAKER_19]: Briefly you, sir.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think you'd be more likely to actually win that overall majority if you treated voters with the intelligence they have and answered their questions in terms of what ifs and what might happen if there was a coalition that needed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Treat people with their intelligence.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think that it's fair
[SPEAKER_19]: in the last seven days to do everything you can to try and win.
[SPEAKER_19]: I want to use the limited time I've got, including the 28 minutes tonight, to explain why a Conservative majority government would be good for Britain.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think we'd go further and faster in clearing the deficit, in building those homes, in providing those pensions.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's what I want to do.
[SPEAKER_18]: You've had your 28 minutes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Let me make this point.
[SPEAKER_19]: People know with me, if we fall short,
[SPEAKER_19]: I will do the right thing for the country.
[SPEAKER_19]: I did last time, I would again, but I would still plead with people with seven days to go, particularly when you're faced with the alternative of a Labour government backed by the SNP, people who don't even want our country to succeed or even exist.
[SPEAKER_19]: When that's the alternative, put your trust in 23 more seats for the Conservatives and we can have a very strong and very clear government.
[SPEAKER_19]: David Cameron, thank you very much indeed.
[SPEAKER_18]: So, our next party leader is from the Labour Party.
[SPEAKER_18]: The leader of the Labour Party, would you welcome Ed Miliband, please?
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_18]: Mr Miliband, the first question is from Elizabeth Moody, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Elizabeth Moody.
[SPEAKER_38]: Good evening, Mr Miliband.
[SPEAKER_38]: Five years ago, the outgoing Labour Treasury Minister left a message.
[SPEAKER_38]: There's no money left.
[SPEAKER_38]: How can we trust the Labour Party with the UK economy?
[SPEAKER_18]: We just saw it, by the way.
[SPEAKER_17]: David Cameron carried it in his pocket and produced it.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think it's his regular prop.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me directly address you, Elizabeth.
[SPEAKER_17]: There was a global financial crisis.
[SPEAKER_17]: There was a high deficit.
[SPEAKER_17]: That deficit hasn't been cleared.
[SPEAKER_17]: It will be the mission of my government to cut the deficit every year and balance the books.
[SPEAKER_17]: And let me tell you how I'm going to do it.
[SPEAKER_17]: First of all, we'll have fair taxes.
[SPEAKER_17]: So we'll reverse David Cameron's tax cut for the richest in our society, millionaires.
[SPEAKER_17]: I can't justify a £43,000 tax cut for every millionaire in Britain.
[SPEAKER_17]: Secondly, we'll protect key areas like health and education, but outside those key areas there will be falls in spending because we've got to get the deficit down.
[SPEAKER_17]: But the final thing concerns your living standards.
[SPEAKER_17]: We've seen living standards fall over this Parliament.
[SPEAKER_17]: As a result, lower living standards means lower tax revenues for government, and that's why the deficit hasn't been cleared.
[SPEAKER_17]: So it's a three-part plan to make sure we balance the books.
[SPEAKER_18]: But if you look back, and the question was looking back, why should we trust Labour in the light of what happened before, for six years before the crash, you increased borrowing, year on year on year on year.
[SPEAKER_18]: So why should people believe that they're going to get it done?
[SPEAKER_17]: The debt and the deficit were both lower before the financial crisis, but let me direct... Of course they were, but you were increasing
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, let me address directly the issue about the financial crisis.
[SPEAKER_17]: We got it wrong on bank regulation.
[SPEAKER_17]: Look, the mistake we made, and I absolutely say this to this audience, was the banks weren't properly regulated.
[SPEAKER_17]: We made that mistake.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, the question you've got to consider for the future is who's going to get it right for the future.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, we've learnt that lesson.
[SPEAKER_17]: So happens David Cameron was saying there should be less bank regulation at a time, but leave that to one side.
[SPEAKER_17]: We've learnt that lesson for the future.
[SPEAKER_17]: And look, I'm the first Labour leader, David, going into an election saying spending in key areas is actually going to fall.
[SPEAKER_17]: That's because I'm so determined, back to Elizabeth, that we live within our means.
[SPEAKER_40]: Just getting back to your letter for a moment, the letter that Mr Cameron you call is a prop.
[SPEAKER_40]: I run a business here in Leeds.
[SPEAKER_40]: The last five years have been really hard work but we've got a plan now and the economy is improving.
[SPEAKER_40]: What worries me is you're about to put Ed Balls back in as a Chancellor and he called that letter a joke.
[SPEAKER_40]: Now let me tell you, running a business the last few years is anything but a joke and if that's the way your party wants to treat the economy, how can we trust you?
[SPEAKER_17]: May I ask what your business does?
[SPEAKER_40]: I run a marketing business.
[SPEAKER_40]: I employ 76 people here in this city.
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, let me tell you very specifically what I think we need to do for businesses like yours.
[SPEAKER_17]: And this does go to the big choice at this election.
[SPEAKER_17]: There'll be some people who tell you that the way we succeed as a country is as long as a few people at the top do well and large corporations, that's what powers the economy.
[SPEAKER_17]: Look, I've got a different view and that's your choice for the next five years.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think it's when working people, when every person in our country succeeds, that Britain succeeds.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now for your business, we'd make a different choice from Mr Cameron.
[SPEAKER_17]: He wants to cut taxes further for the largest businesses.
[SPEAKER_17]: I would cut your business rates if I was Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now that's important, I hope, for your business, but I think it tells a bigger story about how Britain succeeds.
[SPEAKER_17]: And as I say, I think it succeeds not just with a few successful corporations, but with millions of businesses and millions of working people.
[SPEAKER_18]: Does that satisfy you?
[SPEAKER_40]: No it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_40]: That wasn't the question I asked you.
[SPEAKER_40]: I asked you why on earth I should trust a Chancellor who thinks a letter like that was a joke.
[SPEAKER_40]: If he worked in the corporate world he would have been fired and he would not be allowed back to do that job.
[SPEAKER_40]: And you're telling me he can do it.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me tell you, I can tell you, Ed Balls takes incredibly seriously the need to get the deficit down.
[SPEAKER_17]: That was it while I was at the front page of our manifesto.
[SPEAKER_17]: That's why he as Shadow Chancellor is going into this election telling all of our colleagues in lots of these departments that spending is going to fall.
[SPEAKER_17]: You'll have to make your decision but we are absolutely deadly serious about getting the deficit down and balancing the books.
[SPEAKER_40]: I also think, Mr Miliband, you talk about big businesses.
[SPEAKER_40]: I was today with the biggest private employer in the UK, which is Tesco.
[SPEAKER_40]: They've had a pretty tough time, but they talked about behaving their way out of the problems they've made.
[SPEAKER_40]: And I think that's something that politicians have got to think about too.
[SPEAKER_17]: We need strong big business in this country.
[SPEAKER_17]: We do, and one thing, can I just come in on that David?
[SPEAKER_17]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_17]: But one thing I think business needs, and again this is a difference of view, I think we need to stay within the European Union.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because I think it would be a disaster for our businesses.
[SPEAKER_17]: I mean, give David Cameron credit, he believes in us staying in the EU, but I'm afraid he's being dragged by his party to exit from the EU.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now again, I've got to say to this audience, I've got to say to this audience, I think that would be a real problem for our country.
[SPEAKER_17]: Alright, the woman up there at the back, yes.
[SPEAKER_37]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_37]: With all the rhetoric about non-DOMs and unpaid tax, if your party were in power, do you think you could ever bridge the gap between the richest and the poorest?
[SPEAKER_17]: What's your name?
[SPEAKER_37]: It's Shirley.
[SPEAKER_17]: Shirley?
[SPEAKER_37]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's a great question, Shirley, and let me answer it directly.
[SPEAKER_17]: Yes, there's this rule that Shirley's referring to called the non-DOM rule.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now some of you may know about it, some of you may not, but basically it means you can live here, work here, be permanently settled here, but not pay taxes here.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's been in place, believe it or not, for 200 years.
[SPEAKER_17]: That's 40 Prime Ministers.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm going to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm going to get rid of it because I believe in a country where there's one rule for all, not one rule for the rich and powerful and another rule for everybody else.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now David Cameron wants to defend that rule.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now I think he's wrong about that.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think we've got to tackle tax avoidance wherever we find it and make people at the top live up to their responsibilities.
[SPEAKER_18]: I hope we can...
[SPEAKER_18]: I hope we can reach the man sitting right behind me here.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: So I've just got a really simple question.
[SPEAKER_20]: Do you accept that when Labour was last in power it overspent?
[SPEAKER_17]: No I don't.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I know you may not agree with that.
[SPEAKER_17]: But let me just say very clearly...
[SPEAKER_18]: Even with all the borrowing?
[SPEAKER_17]: You're on your own?
[SPEAKER_17]: No I don't.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me tell you.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because there are schools that have been rebuilt in our country.
[SPEAKER_17]: There are hospitals that were rebuilt.
[SPEAKER_17]: There were Sure Start centres that were built.
[SPEAKER_17]: which would not have happened.
[SPEAKER_17]: And so, look, I don't agree with that.
[SPEAKER_17]: And let me just explain to you the way I see it.
[SPEAKER_17]: There was a global financial crisis which caused the deficit to rise.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, look, President Obama isn't dealing with a high deficit because we built more schools and hospitals.
[SPEAKER_17]: He's dealing with a high deficit because there was that global financial crisis.
[SPEAKER_17]: But spending's got to fall.
[SPEAKER_17]: I say to this gentleman here, spending's got to fall.
[SPEAKER_17]: And that's why we will reduce spending.
[SPEAKER_16]: All right.
[SPEAKER_16]: And you, sir, there?
[SPEAKER_16]: global financial crisis.
[SPEAKER_16]: Australia didn't suffer this.
[SPEAKER_16]: Canada didn't suffer this.
[SPEAKER_16]: Some of the other major countries didn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_16]: This country suffered because Gordon Brown sold gold just to prop up the social services.
[SPEAKER_16]: How can you stand there and say you didn't overspend and end up bankrupting this country?
[SPEAKER_16]: That is absolutely ludicrous.
[SPEAKER_16]: You're frankly just lying.
[SPEAKER_17]: I guess I'm not going to convince you, but... Well, you're not going to convince me, because the facts speak for themselves.
[SPEAKER_16]: You stood there and said you didn't overspend.
[SPEAKER_16]: If I get to the end of the week and I can't afford to buy a pint, I've overspent.
[SPEAKER_16]: It means I haven't got any money left.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_16]: We've got to the end of a government of 13 years, and during that 13-year period, you spent, spent, you sold gold when it was low.
[SPEAKER_16]: If we still had the gold now, we'd be pretty much better off.
[SPEAKER_16]: You can't stand that and say... Can I just come back on the point that you made?
[SPEAKER_17]: I think I'm not going to convince you...
[SPEAKER_18]: The point being that it's a millstone round what happened under the last government.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me come back on this because you said something very important which is that some other countries didn't suffer from that.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now that's because they were less exposed to financial services.
[SPEAKER_16]: No, I'm sorry, I mean financial services.
[SPEAKER_16]: Financial services actually put millions and millions and millions of pounds into this country.
[SPEAKER_16]: Millions of pounds, which you then spend, and you spend irresponsibly.
[SPEAKER_17]: because I think that what we didn't do enough of was build up other industries as well.
[SPEAKER_17]: Sure, financial services is important, including here in Leeds.
[SPEAKER_17]: But look, the reality is that we didn't do enough on apprenticeships, we didn't do enough on a modern industrial policy, and we're not doing enough now.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because you can't simply rely on one industry.
[SPEAKER_17]: And so my point is that actually you need a more diverse industrial base, and that is also at stake in this election.
[SPEAKER_18]: All right, I'll come to you.
[SPEAKER_18]: We must keep moving around the audience here.
[SPEAKER_18]: I don't want two or three people to...
[SPEAKER_23]: If you can't accept that you overspent in the last government, then why on earth should we trust you not to do it again?
[SPEAKER_23]: If you can't even realise that that's what you did, and they've cut the deficit by half, why should we trust you not to do the same thing if you can't even accept that you overspent?
[SPEAKER_17]: You and other audience members, and it goes back to Elizabeth's question, will have to make a choice.
[SPEAKER_17]: There are some parties in this election saying no cuts at all.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not saying that.
[SPEAKER_17]: Mr Cameron, or he didn't say this earlier, wants to double the cuts next year.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's not just the same cuts as in the last parliament, double the cuts.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now I think that would be incredibly dangerous for our National Health Service.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because you want to borrow more.
[SPEAKER_23]: You're saying you don't want people from my age group to be in debt and yet you're committing to borrowing even more.
[SPEAKER_17]: No, we're committing to a balance plan which balances the books, not going much further.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I tried to set out what that balance plan is, but look, you and others will have to make a judgement about this, because I think we can balance the books without sacrificing our public services, without sacrificing tax credits.
[SPEAKER_17]: Jenny asked a question earlier, the very first question of this programme, where is Jenny who asked?
[SPEAKER_17]: who asked the question.
[SPEAKER_17]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_17]: Look, Jenny, I'm afraid David Cameron, he might have sounded like he answered your question, but he didn't.
[SPEAKER_17]: But he didn't really give you a guarantee.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm going to give you that guarantee tonight.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not going to cut your tax credits.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not going to cut child benefit or means test it.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think that would be the wrong thing to do for our country.
[SPEAKER_17]: the wrong thing to do for family financing.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I've got to say, after Mr Cameron's answers tonight, tax credits and child benefit are on the ballot paper of this election.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because millions of families risk losing thousands of pounds because of the cuts plan that he has.
[SPEAKER_17]: So yes, I do disagree with Mr Cameron.
[SPEAKER_17]: I've got a different plan.
[SPEAKER_18]: I think we should move on to another subject.
[SPEAKER_18]: Simon Wilkinson, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Simon Wilkinson.
[SPEAKER_33]: Why is the Labour Party misleading the country about having to do a deal with the SNP in the event of a minority Labour government?
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me be plain.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're not going to do a deal with the Scottish National Party.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're not going to have a coalition.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're not going to have a deal.
[SPEAKER_17]: And let me just say this to you, Simon.
[SPEAKER_17]: If it meant we weren't going to be in government, not doing a coalition, not having a deal, then so be it.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not going to sacrifice the future of our country, the unity of our country.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not going to give in to SNP demands around Trident, around the deficit, or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_17]: So I just want to repeat this point to you.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not going to have a Labour government if it means deals or coalitions with the Scottish National Party.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I just want to say this to voters in Scotland, David.
[SPEAKER_17]: There's no easy route here to vote SNP and get a Labour government.
[SPEAKER_17]: If you want a Labour government, you need to vote Labour.
[SPEAKER_33]: So when other members of the Shadow Cabinet say that they're open to deals, you disagree with that?
[SPEAKER_33]: I do, and I'm the leader.
[SPEAKER_33]: We're not going to have deals.
[SPEAKER_33]: And you wouldn't put forward a Queen's speech on the hope that they'd support it?
[SPEAKER_33]: You just wouldn't go to the Queen and accept her invitation?
[SPEAKER_33]: We do want to put forward a Labour Queen's speech.
[SPEAKER_17]: I want a majority Labour government, and it'll be for parties in the House of Commons to vote for it.
[SPEAKER_17]: But you ask me about deals, you ask me about coalitions, they're not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_17]: I couldn't be clearer with you.
[SPEAKER_18]: You said something rather interesting then.
[SPEAKER_18]: You said you'd rather not have a Labour government than have a Labour government supported by the SNP?
[SPEAKER_17]: A Labour government with a coalition or a deal?
[SPEAKER_17]: What is a deal in your terms?
[SPEAKER_17]: I've been asked about lots of different kinds of deals.
[SPEAKER_17]: Coalition, what they call confidence and supply.
[SPEAKER_17]: The coalition you've explained, which is ministers in your cabinet.
[SPEAKER_17]: But what is a deal?
[SPEAKER_17]: Confidence and supply, they've said, which is where you sort of have an arrangement.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not doing that.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I want to explain why I'm not doing it.
[SPEAKER_18]: So you'd rather lose office, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_18]: You'd rather not have a Labour government than do that.
[SPEAKER_17]: If the price of having a Labour government was a coalition or a deal with the Scottish National Party, it's not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_18]: OK.
[SPEAKER_18]: Anyone want to comment?
[SPEAKER_18]: No, you've spoken already.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes, you, sir, there, in the middle.
[SPEAKER_18]: I'd like to have people who haven't spoken already.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: In that case, does that rule out a future Labour government?
[SPEAKER_13]: Because you're not going to win the most seats in the UK.
[SPEAKER_17]: First of all, I don't want to sound like the previous bloke, Mr Cameron, but I am working for a majority Labour government.
[SPEAKER_17]: But look, I'm going to fight as hard as I can, for as many seats as I can, and then it'll be for the House of Commons to decide who's in government.
[SPEAKER_17]: I just want to make this point about the SNP, and the same applies to a party like UKIP.
[SPEAKER_17]: The reason why I reject the SNP...
[SPEAKER_17]: I mean, they're, by the way, fighting us in Scotland, so the notion that we're sort of friends with the SNP is obviously nonsense.
[SPEAKER_17]: They're our die-hard opponents.
[SPEAKER_17]: the reason I reject it is because they want to break up the country and not only that they used to say that the referendum was a once-in-a-lifetime experience that's what they said before the last referendum and now Nicola Sturgeon is opening the door to another referendum in the next five years that's why I'm not going to have a coalition or a deal with them.
[SPEAKER_17]: And the woman there on the gangway?
[SPEAKER_21]: The problem is, you do sound a lot like the other guy, because both of you seem to not entertain the possibility that you might not get a majority, which is absolutely ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_21]: And you really need to be honest with voters about what you might do in the event that you don't.
[SPEAKER_17]: What was your name, I'm sorry?
[SPEAKER_21]: Rebecca.
[SPEAKER_17]: Rebecca, let me try and do better than the other guy on this one.
[SPEAKER_17]: You know, he was saying at the end, David Cameron, that if you didn't get a majority, it meant this business of going into a darkened room with Nick Clegg.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, I don't like the sound of that at all, for a whole range of reasons.
[SPEAKER_17]: But I don't like it for one particular reason.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm not going to start bartering away my manifesto, whatever the outcome of the election.
[SPEAKER_17]: Even if I don't win a majority, I've got a manifesto.
[SPEAKER_17]: Some of you may have read it, not that many people, but some people may have read it.
[SPEAKER_17]: The manifesto's out there.
[SPEAKER_17]: If I'm the Prime Minister, I'm going to do everything I can to get my manifesto, not start trading for Nick Clegg or anyone else's manifesto.
[SPEAKER_17]: And so, you know, I think we're in a sort of new world in Britain.
[SPEAKER_17]: It was the first coalition, obviously, this coalition, that they'd been for a long time.
[SPEAKER_17]: But in my view, if we don't have a majority government, it is not about saying, go into a darkened room with somebody and then start lopping off bits of your manifesto.
[SPEAKER_17]: That isn't what you're voting for.
[SPEAKER_17]: That isn't what Labour voters are voting for.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's not going to happen if I'm Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_18]: All right, we'll go to another subject.
[SPEAKER_18]: Elisha Lynas, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Elisha Lynas.
[SPEAKER_35]: What makes your view more important than the British people when it comes to the EU and an in-out referendum?
[SPEAKER_17]: Where is Elisha?
[SPEAKER_17]: Oh, there.
[SPEAKER_35]: It's actually Elisha.
[SPEAKER_17]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_17]: Elisha.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's about leadership, Alicia.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's about leadership and what I want to achieve as Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_17]: When I look at the country, what do I think the biggest problems in the country are?
[SPEAKER_17]: I think five years of wages falling behind bills and the threat it's going to happen again.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think five years of young people thinking they're going to have a worse life than their parents.
[SPEAKER_17]: And five years of an NHS in crisis.
[SPEAKER_17]: And if I'm Prime Minister, in seven or eight days' time, I want to spend all of my energies on those issues, not on deciding whether we want to exit the European Union, which I think, frankly, would be a disaster for the country and would set us back.
[SPEAKER_17]: But supposing she wants a voice vote?
[SPEAKER_35]: Yeah, so your view is more important than mine and everybody else here?
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, it isn't...
[SPEAKER_17]: I do respect that point of view, but I don't agree with it, because I'm putting my view forward.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I think one of the things you've got to do... Then let us put ours forward.
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, you do at the general election.
[SPEAKER_17]: And one of the things about leadership is you don't always do what the polls tell you to do.
[SPEAKER_17]: You do what you think is the right thing for the country.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I've got to level with you and level with the country that I don't think the right thing for our country to do now is to plunge ourselves into two years of debating whether to leave the EU when I've got to tell you that for jobs and the millions of jobs that depend on it, for businesses and for families, it will be a disaster.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, there's one thing I will say to you, which is if there's any further transfer of powers from Britain to the European Union, we would have a referendum.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think it's unlikely to happen, though.
[SPEAKER_17]: So, you know, in a way, you've got to make your own judgment about what is the most important issue to you.
[SPEAKER_17]: For me, it isn't trying to get out of the EU.
OK?
[SPEAKER_48]: So you don't want an EU referendum and all the debate that brings, but a second election because you won't form a majority government?
[SPEAKER_17]: I don't want a second election either.
[SPEAKER_48]: Yeah, but if you don't get a majority, the Conservatives don't get a majority, you're not going to go with the SNP.
[SPEAKER_48]: I want to govern.
[SPEAKER_17]: I want to govern and change the country.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I think, I've just got to say to you, the stakes are incredibly high.
[SPEAKER_17]: You get this choice once every five years.
[SPEAKER_17]: Do you want a country run for the richest and most powerful, the non-Doms that the lady talked about at the top, defending the non-Doms, while for Jenny, her tax credits aren't safe.
[SPEAKER_17]: That's the choice at this election.
[SPEAKER_18]: That is the choice facing the British people.
[SPEAKER_18]: A couple more people.
[SPEAKER_18]: The woman there and then I'll come to you and then we'll move on.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_12]: The Conservative Party have made cuts to education, adults and further education.
[SPEAKER_12]: How do you propose to undo the damage?
[SPEAKER_18]: You're on education, which we may come to.
[SPEAKER_18]: I want to stick to the subject of the EU, if you don't mind, while we're on it.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes, you, sir.
[SPEAKER_15]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_15]: Mr Miliband.
[SPEAKER_15]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_15]: Can I just ask you, you know when people ask you a question about forming a coalition, and you say, no, I want a majority, and Mr Cameron said the same.
[SPEAKER_15]: Do you comprehend how much respect you would get from the audience if you were truly honest?
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, look, sir, I'm saying to you...
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm absolutely not saying to you I'm guaranteed a majority, I'm working for it, and I guess you'll respect me saying that, but I tried to answer the lady on the end who asked the question about the circumstances of not getting a majority, and I tried to outline my approach.
[SPEAKER_17]: And as I said, my approach is not to start to barter away different bits of the manifesto.
[SPEAKER_17]: And the reason I say that is because I think trust in politics, which is a pretty fragile thing anyway, is incredibly low.
[SPEAKER_17]: And so the idea that Nick Clegg says, I'm breaking my tuition fees promise, and David Cameron says I'm breaking my VAT promise, and they blame each other and the coalition, that's not going to be my approach whatever the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_17]: If I'm Prime Minister, I'm going to seek to implement all of my manifesto.
[SPEAKER_18]: I'm going to go back to the lady there.
[SPEAKER_18]: Just one brief question on this and an answer if you would.
[SPEAKER_12]: Conservative Party have made up to 24% cuts in adults and further education.
[SPEAKER_12]: How do you propose to undo the damage done by the savage cuts to adult education made by this government?
[SPEAKER_17]: Have you had experience of this?
[SPEAKER_12]: Yes, we have.
[SPEAKER_12]: I work in FE.
[SPEAKER_17]: What we've said for the future, I can't guarantee to reverse what's already been done, but what we've said for the future is that we will protect education spending.
[SPEAKER_17]: So it will be protected at least against inflation.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, the reason why we've made that choice, which we haven't made in other government departments, is because I think investing in education, investing in the future, is essential not just for our society but for our economy as well.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because I think it's a false economy to start cutting back on education spending.
[SPEAKER_17]: So I can't promise to immediately reverse the damage and I'm not going to make a false promise to you.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's for adults in further education, not for universities or primaries.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes indeed, we have made that point.
[SPEAKER_28]: Mr. Miliband, is a vote for you carte blanche to see the Welfare Bill skyrocket?
[SPEAKER_28]: I'm over here.
[SPEAKER_17]: Hi, sorry.
[SPEAKER_28]: It's OK. Is a vote for yourself, carte blanche, to see the Welfare Bill skyrocket?
[SPEAKER_17]: No.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me explain why.
[SPEAKER_17]: I believe in a welfare system with responsibility.
[SPEAKER_17]: Responsibility means that if you can work, you should work.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're the only party at this election actually putting forward a proposal to say if you're a young person unemployed more than a year, we'll guarantee you a job working with the private sector, but if you don't take the job you'll lose benefits.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because I think that actually responsibility is the foundation of the welfare system.
[SPEAKER_17]: But let me just say one other thing to you, Amy, because it's important for keeping control of the welfare bill.
[SPEAKER_17]: Take the issue of housing benefit.
[SPEAKER_17]: You may not be obvious, but the housing benefit bill has gone up a lot in the last five years for those in work.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, the reason for that is we have an economy based on low pay, and we're not building enough homes in our country.
[SPEAKER_17]: That's why we'll have an £8 minimum wage, and that's why we'll build homes again in Britain.
[SPEAKER_17]: You see, dealing with the welfare bill is about responsibility, but it's also about tackling the underlying factors that are driving the welfare bill up, like a low-pay economy that doesn't work for working people.
[SPEAKER_17]: And you know, this is all connected.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because our economy doesn't work for most people and works for the richest in our society, in my view, it means that the welfare bill is higher.
[SPEAKER_17]: It means that people are having a harder life and working all the hours that God sends.
[SPEAKER_17]: So we'll keep it under control.
[SPEAKER_28]: But doesn't your party believe that benefits are a legitimate lifestyle choice?
[SPEAKER_17]: No.
[SPEAKER_28]: I think that they do.
[SPEAKER_28]: You say about raising minimum wage and you're going to guarantee jobs.
[SPEAKER_28]: I work in recruitment.
[SPEAKER_28]: Where are those jobs going to come from?
[SPEAKER_17]: They're going to come from working with the private sector to help create those jobs.
[SPEAKER_17]: Apprenticeships for our young people, so that actually there are the skilled people that the private sector needs.
[SPEAKER_17]: A proper industrial policy, which will help the private sector.
[SPEAKER_17]: Cutting business rates, which will also help grow the economy and help grow jobs.
[SPEAKER_17]: Leading in the big industries of the future, like green industry.
[SPEAKER_17]: Take climate change for example.
[SPEAKER_17]: Look, some people see that as a burden.
[SPEAKER_17]: It isn't a burden, it's a necessity to tackle it, but it's a chance for us to lead as a country in one of the most important industries of the future.
[SPEAKER_18]: Can we come back to welfare?
[SPEAKER_18]: Is your plan to cut the welfare bill, to increase it or keep it as it is?
[SPEAKER_17]: There's a cap on the welfare bill which the government has put in place, we're going to keep to within that cap.
[SPEAKER_18]: Because the IFS says that your commitment to being tough on welfare amounts to almost nothing.
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, I don't agree with them.
[SPEAKER_18]: Where have they gone wrong?
[SPEAKER_17]: Because they've analysed everybody's thing, everybody's spending, everybody's child.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me give you an example.
[SPEAKER_17]: Look, you know, I want to help pensioners in our country.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're going to have the triple lock on the basic state pension.
[SPEAKER_17]: That means pensions going up by 2.5% or prices or earnings.
[SPEAKER_17]: But we have said that the winter fuel allowance will not continue to go to pensioners with incomes above £43,000 a year.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because I don't think I can justify that in the times that we're in.
[SPEAKER_17]: But I think this point about the
[SPEAKER_17]: drivers of the welfare bill and what is actually making it go up is actually the key thing that is underlying it.
[SPEAKER_18]: I'll go to the woman with spectacles there at the back.
[SPEAKER_18]: I'm trying to go to different people who haven't spoken yet.
[SPEAKER_42]: Are you essentially telling us that you're expecting the private sector to fund the gaps in the welfare bill because there's only so much that employers can actually do to, you know, you can't keep expecting, you're talking about zero hours contracts, changes, you're talking about
[SPEAKER_42]: getting people on to working in the private sector after a year.
[SPEAKER_42]: How are employers supposed to afford all of this stuff?
[SPEAKER_42]: Because being an employer is a very, very expensive business as it is.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're definitely not expecting employers to fund the welfare bill.
[SPEAKER_17]: But my point at the moment is that the welfare bill is actually spending billions and billions of pounds subsidising low pay in our country.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I'm afraid that's the sort of reality.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now we've got to raise the minimum wage in a way that is cautious, because we've got to do it so it doesn't put people out of work, and that's what we'll do.
[SPEAKER_17]: But I think we've also got to confront the fact that because we're one of the low-pay capitals of Europe, we are spending tens of billions of pounds on welfare as a result of that.
[SPEAKER_17]: So it's about working with the private sector to make sure you can raise wages.
[SPEAKER_17]: Alright, on that point let me bring in Chris Magee, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Chris Magee.
[SPEAKER_11]: A ban on zero-hours contracts will prevent me from growing my small business.
[SPEAKER_11]: Isn't it time the Labour Party put business before gimmicks and soundbites?
[SPEAKER_18]: And there is evidence that more people like zero-hours contracts than dislike them.
[SPEAKER_18]: Chris, what's your business?
[SPEAKER_11]: It's a tourism business, so when the sun shines, I've got business.
[SPEAKER_11]: If the sun doesn't shine, I don't, so...
[SPEAKER_11]: The sun always shines in Yorkshire.
[SPEAKER_17]: Yeah, always.
[SPEAKER_17]: Whenever there's a cycle race, there is.
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, let me tell you about our policy, Chris, and then maybe you come back and say how it might affect you.
[SPEAKER_17]: Our policy is this, which is that after 12 weeks, an employee will have a right to a regular contract, not a zero-hours contract, based on the average number of hours that they've done.
[SPEAKER_17]: And if the employee wants to carry on with the zero-hours contract, they can, but we think that should be in the hands of the employee having the right to the regular contract.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me just explain why I say that.
[SPEAKER_17]: And I know this may be difficult for your business, but let me just explain the reasons for that.
[SPEAKER_17]: I don't think we can base the future of our economy on the idea, and I meet lots of people on zero-hours contracts, that people don't know from one day to the next how many hours they're doing or what wage they're going to be getting.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because I don't... Mr Cameron was honest enough to say the other day he couldn't live on a zero-hours contract.
[SPEAKER_17]: Well, nor could I.
[SPEAKER_17]: But if I can't live on it and he can't live on it, I don't think we should make the British people live on one.
[SPEAKER_17]: All right.
[SPEAKER_17]: One last question, if we can... That's the logic of my position.
[SPEAKER_18]: Ryan... Ryan Furlong, please.
[SPEAKER_11]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_11]: What are you going to do differently about immigration?
[SPEAKER_17]: I've changed Labour's position and let me tell you what we're going to do.
[SPEAKER_17]: Under a Labour government, when people come here, they won't get benefits for at least the first two years.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're going to ensure that in our public services, people learn English.
[SPEAKER_17]: In fact, I think everybody who comes here should learn English.
[SPEAKER_17]: And thirdly, we're going to stop something which I think, frankly, should have been stopped a long time ago, which is employers bringing people into this country, exploiting migrant labour, and undercutting wages.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let me just give you a fact, Brian.
[SPEAKER_17]: There have been...
[SPEAKER_17]: There have been two prosecutions for failure to pay the minimum wage in the last five years.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, the notion that that reflects what's actually happening in the world of work is, of course, nonsense.
[SPEAKER_17]: And even the government's own Migration Advisory Committee have said that is one of the things that is bringing low-skilled labour into here.
[SPEAKER_17]: The notion that some rogue employers, and I emphasize some because most employers don't do this, can get away with bringing migrant labour in and undercutting wages.
[SPEAKER_17]: So, the last thing I want to say to you is this.
[SPEAKER_17]: You know, I don't believe it's prejudice to worry about immigration.
[SPEAKER_17]: Some people say it is, I don't believe it is.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think people's concerns are real.
[SPEAKER_17]: I see it in my own constituency in Doncaster and we're going to deal with people's concerns with real controls.
[SPEAKER_18]: Why won't you set a target then?
[SPEAKER_25]: refused to set a target when she criticises the Conservative policy on it but isn't willing to commit to any kind of number at all.
[SPEAKER_25]: Is it just free-for-all?
[SPEAKER_25]: Everyone who wants to come here can come here regardless of economic suitability or affordability and where is everyone going to live?
[SPEAKER_17]: What's your name?
[SPEAKER_25]: Jo.
[SPEAKER_17]: Joe, I'll tell you why I'm not going to set a target, because I don't want to stand on the stage in five years' time and try and explain why I've broken my promise.
[SPEAKER_17]: This is a really important point.
[SPEAKER_17]: David Cameron stood on the stage five years ago and said he'd get net migration to the tens of thousands.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's now 298,000.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let him answer Joe.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because Joe, I'm not going to pluck a target out of the air.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's not the right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because I can't guarantee I'm going to meet it.
[SPEAKER_17]: And you know, this goes to a point about trust in politics.
[SPEAKER_17]: Trust is so low in politics, for reasons I understand, because of broken promises in the past.
[SPEAKER_17]: I want to be the first politician to under-promise and over-deliver, not over-promise and under-deliver.
[SPEAKER_17]: And look, sometimes that means I'll get a hard time from people like Joe because I'm not making the easy promise.
[SPEAKER_17]: But I'm not the guy who's going to make the easy promises.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because all it does is it makes people think you're all going to break your promises.
[SPEAKER_18]: All right, we've got... No, no, no, I'm afraid...
[SPEAKER_18]: I'm afraid we've come to the end of those 28 minutes that he's had.
[SPEAKER_17]: It flew by for me, anyway.
[SPEAKER_17]: Maybe not for the audience.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you very much, Mr Lelen.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_18]: So the last of our three leaders now from the Liberal Democrat party, the leader of the Liberal Democrats, would you welcome Nick Clegg.
[SPEAKER_18]: And Mr Clegg, the first question comes from Darren Metcalfe, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Darren Metcalfe.
[SPEAKER_08]: Nick.
[SPEAKER_08]: Hi Darren.
[SPEAKER_08]: Hiya.
[SPEAKER_08]: Your promise on student loans has destroyed your reputation.
[SPEAKER_20]: Why would we ever believe anything else you say?
[SPEAKER_20]: look firstly I got it wrong I said sorry musically no less I when you make a mistake in politics just as in life in politics just as in life sometimes you can't do exactly what you want I was absolutely between a rock and a hard place five years ago on that particular policy secondly I hope you can
[SPEAKER_20]: You can at least give me credit for the many, many other things that I have actually put into practice, whether it's taking lots of people on low pay out of paying any income tax, the biggest expansion of apprenticeships this country's ever seen, the biggest reform of our pension system in a generation, more money into schools to help with the education of disadvantaged children, more childcare, shared parental leave, healthy lunches for little kids at primary school, the list goes on.
[SPEAKER_20]: Look, I accept that for some people, and you may be one of them,
[SPEAKER_18]: for whom that one thing you can't forgive, you can't forget.
[SPEAKER_20]: What happened, as you may remember, was the previous government, the Labour government, introduced fees and then increased them.
[SPEAKER_20]: When we came into government, there was no money left.
[SPEAKER_20]: David Cameron's just been waving around the letter which was provided to the Liberal Democrat Chief Secretary of the Treasury at the time, saying there was no money left.
[SPEAKER_20]: And both the larger parties, as they, I think, would admit if you'd asked them about it, wanted fees to go up very, very considerably.
[SPEAKER_20]: In fact, the report commissioned at the time into all of this said there should be no upper limit at all.
[SPEAKER_20]: In a sense what we did was get the fairest deal we could in those circumstances and thankfully now got more young people at university than ever before.
[SPEAKER_20]: But look, as I said earlier, my experience is some people absolutely will say, you know, we can't forget that.
[SPEAKER_20]: I hope there are plenty of other fair-minded folk who will accept that nonetheless there are many, many, many other good policies that I did put into practice.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes, you in the centre.
[SPEAKER_07]: The policy of increasing tuition fees is essentially robbing from the rich to give them a sense of you're taking money away from future generations to go to university because the economy is going to be so bust by people not repaying their fees, never getting enough money to be able to meet the threshold, that the policy itself is completely defunct.
[SPEAKER_20]: No, I don't agree with that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Under the old system we inherited, if you left university you had to start repaying the moment you earned £15,000.
[SPEAKER_20]: Now you don't pay back if you earn 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.
[SPEAKER_20]: You only start paying back when you earn... That's precisely my point.
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, you're right.
[SPEAKER_20]: Some people say it's not generous enough.
[SPEAKER_20]: You're saying it's too generous.
[SPEAKER_20]: You're right to say that no one needs to pay up front.
[SPEAKER_20]: There were thousands of students under the old system who used to have to pay up front or ask their parents to do so.
[SPEAKER_20]: And crucially, if you can't pay it off during your working life, it gets paid off for you.
[SPEAKER_20]: So, in a sense, it's a much, much more fair system.
[SPEAKER_20]: It's not the system I would have liked, but it's a much, much more fair system than people alleged at the time when it was introduced.
[SPEAKER_18]: The question was about trust.
[SPEAKER_18]: You, sir, in the blue pullover there with the tie.
[SPEAKER_18]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_18]: In the second row from the back.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hi, Mr. Clegg.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_10]: The public suggests they can't forgive...
[SPEAKER_18]: So, Prime Minister Clegg...
[SPEAKER_10]: No.
[SPEAKER_18]: I thought you said Prime Minister Clegg for a moment.
[SPEAKER_10]: The public suggests they can't forgive that one thing.
[SPEAKER_10]: So if hindsight, would you go into coalition in 2010 again?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_20]: In fact, the more I look back on it, the more proud I am that I think it was a difficult decision.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think it was a brave decision for the Liberal Democrats.
[SPEAKER_20]: It's come at short-term political cost.
[SPEAKER_20]: But I'm absolutely clear in my mind that if you think back to 2010, we could have been Greece.
[SPEAKER_20]: We could have been Greece.
[SPEAKER_20]: Our deficit was almost as big as Greece's.
[SPEAKER_20]: Our banking crisis was a whole lot worse.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I certainly wouldn't have wanted on my conscience higher interest rates, higher unemployment, higher youth unemployment, which I'm absolutely sure would have happened if we hadn't stepped up to the plate to create a stable government, without which an economic recovery is not possible.
[SPEAKER_20]: And my great concern at the moment
[SPEAKER_20]: is that having got this far over five years and millions of people across the country having made huge sacrifices to get us this far after that terrible heart attack in our economy back in 2008, that we undo it all by lurching off to the right with ideological hardline cuts or lurching off to the left borrowing pots of money that we can't afford.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think we need to remain anchored in the centre ground so that we can finish the job of balancing the books but do it fairly.
[SPEAKER_18]: All right, well, let's deal with where the Liberal Democrats might be with a question from Bethany Cowling, please, after this election.
[SPEAKER_18]: Bethany.
[SPEAKER_27]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_27]: Is leaking details that you're only privy to as part of a coalition likely to get you invited into a coalition again?
[SPEAKER_16]: What are you referring to?
[SPEAKER_27]: So, some details have been leaked today about a policy that was put forward by the Conservatives whilst you were in coalition with them.
[SPEAKER_20]: It's hardly leaked.
[SPEAKER_20]: Danny Alexander said it to The Nation.
[SPEAKER_20]: I mean, he's just saying, quite rightly, that unless the Conservatives come clean, and I don't think David Cameron's done it this evening, where they're going to take the equivalent of £1,500 off eight million of the most vulnerable families, we can only assume that they're looking at the kind of plans which they floated some years ago.
[SPEAKER_20]: If they're ruling that out now...
[SPEAKER_18]: Sorry, did you know about it when it happened?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, but if they're ruling that out...
[SPEAKER_18]: But we didn't know, it only came out today, that's what she means.
[SPEAKER_18]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_18]: It was something you discovered and worked on in coalition, which is being kept secret until today, when Danny Alexander suddenly announced it as a way of attacking the Tory party.
[SPEAKER_20]: Last autumn, George Osborne made a speech at the Conservative Party conference, and he said that the Conservative Party, in a radical departure from the sensible way which we have adopted over the last five years to...
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm not going to ask the very wealthy in society to pay a single extra penny in tax to balance the books and instead only the working age poor are going to pick up the tab for the mistakes made by the bankers.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think that's unfair.
[SPEAKER_20]: They've said they want to take the equivalent of £1,500 off the 8 million poorest families in this country.
[SPEAKER_20]: They won't tell you how they'll do that.
[SPEAKER_20]: £12 billion is about exactly as much as we spend as a country on disability living allowance.
[SPEAKER_20]: Are they going to scrap disability allowance?
[SPEAKER_20]: They're not going to touch child benefit.
[SPEAKER_20]: Are they going to scrap this allowance?
[SPEAKER_20]: It's about the same as we spend on employment support allowance.
[SPEAKER_20]: Are they going to scrap that?
[SPEAKER_20]: I think the point that Danny was making, quite rightly, is we've had five weeks of this election campaign.
[SPEAKER_20]: The Conservatives have a very unfair plan to balance the books, which departs from what we've done in coalition.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I think we are entitled to say, what are you going to do?
[SPEAKER_20]: Who are you going to hurt?
[SPEAKER_20]: Who is going to bear the pain?
[SPEAKER_20]: OK, the woman up there, the back row.
[SPEAKER_26]: But I don't think voters want to hear reasons why not to vote for another party.
[SPEAKER_26]: We want reasons why to vote for your party.
[SPEAKER_20]: That's fair, but I think also voters want to know what the choices are.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I think at the moment the fundamental choices are a Conservative plan, as I've just described, which I think wants to balance the books, which we must do, but wants to do so unfairly, and a Labour plan, which still won't give you any timetable or any detail or any plan about how to balance the books in the first place.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think one of the most important things, whoever is in government, in whatever combination, and by the way, unlike Ed Binnaban and David Cameron, alas, I'm not pretending I'm going to be Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_20]: a
[SPEAKER_20]: in the decisions about how we govern ourselves after next Thursday, when you've cast your vote, one of the most important questions is how do you finish the job of wiping the slate clean so that our kids and our grandkids don't continue to pay the price for our generation's debts, but you do so fairly.
[SPEAKER_20]: And that's why I think the centre-ground position from the Liberal Democrats makes more sense than excessive cuts or excessive borrowing on either side.
[SPEAKER_18]: Somebody's got to be Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_18]: Who are you going to make Prime Minister if you're in a position to decide between those two parties?
[SPEAKER_20]: Look, here's the most unsurprising assertion of the evening.
[SPEAKER_20]: Either David Cameron or Ed Miliband are going to be Prime Ministers.
[SPEAKER_20]: Do you think?
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, yes, I do.
[SPEAKER_18]: Well, there may be no Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_18]: It may be so badly mashed about by the election that nobody can form a majority.
[SPEAKER_20]: Everybody's got to behave in a grown-up, responsible way, even if they don't during the election campaign.
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, we heard Ed Miliband here saying he wouldn't depend on the Scottish National Party.
[SPEAKER_20]: Shall I try and answer the question?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: David Cameron or Ed Miliband are going to walk into Number 10 as Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't think that's much in doubt, and you have to decide which of those two.
[SPEAKER_20]: The real question is, who's going to go in there alongside them?
[SPEAKER_20]: Is it going to be Alex Salmond?
[SPEAKER_20]: Is it going to be Nigel Farage or is it going to be me and the Liberal Democrats?
[SPEAKER_20]: And my great fear, as I was saying earlier, is if you have David Cameron dancing to the tune of Nigel Farage, or the swivel-eyed brigade on the right wing of the Conservative Party, or you have Ed Miliband basically at the beck and call of Alex Salmond, you lurch off to the right and the left, which is not what we need as a country.
[SPEAKER_47]: That's all well and good, but you've just told us that in 2010 you had to make a very difficult decision on tuition fees.
[SPEAKER_47]: How do we know that you won't have to make a very difficult decision again around the things that you're promising us tonight?
[SPEAKER_20]: That's a totally fair challenge and that's why I've been much clearer and
[SPEAKER_20]: I hope, maybe you didn't hear it, about the red lines without which the Liberal Democrats simply won't go into any coalition government.
[SPEAKER_20]: So, for instance, education spending.
[SPEAKER_20]: You just heard Ed Miliband say that the Labour Party wants to increase education spending to keep up with prices.
[SPEAKER_20]: What he didn't tell you is that there are going to be 460,000 new youngsters going into education system.
[SPEAKER_20]: So you need to increase spending to help them as well.
[SPEAKER_20]: The Conservatives want to do the reverse, they want to keep up with increased pupil numbers but not with prices.
[SPEAKER_20]: Both amount to a cut, a multi-billion pound cut to the money that goes into our nurseries, our schools and our colleges.
[SPEAKER_20]: I cannot be more clear with you, the Liberal Democrats will not go into any coalition, any government, we won't sign a coalition agreement unless, if either of those parties insist on those cuts to our education system because I think that really is short-changing the little children of today who should be given just
[SPEAKER_18]: So you mean you want more than just a standstill?
[SPEAKER_18]: Because you've said there are, what is it, 400,000 people coming into education?
[SPEAKER_18]: So you want a big expansion of the education budget, not a standstill?
[SPEAKER_20]: I think the increase in the budget needs to keep pace not only with prices, but also with the increase of the number of children.
[SPEAKER_20]: Do you have any idea what the cost of that would be?
[SPEAKER_20]: It would be another £5 billion by the final year of the next Parliament.
[SPEAKER_20]: And you could find that?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, you think.
[SPEAKER_20]: You, sir.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, I just wondered if you've got plans for a new job after next week when you become unemployed and your party becomes irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Charming.
[SPEAKER_18]: No, I don't.
[SPEAKER_18]: All right, David Jackson.
[SPEAKER_18]: A question from David Jackson, please.
[SPEAKER_06]: Nick, how do you feel about the huge increase of people driven to use food banks, many of them in work poverty or falling foul of benefit sanctions?
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, I think like everybody here, it's very distressing to see an increasing number of people moving to food banks and that's why every day
[SPEAKER_20]: that I have been in government over the last five years as we've had to clear up this unholy mess that we inherited, this massive black hole in our public finances, a broken banking system, the biggest heart attack in our economy in a generation.
[SPEAKER_20]: I've always tried to take decisions where we spread the burden as fairly as possible.
[SPEAKER_20]: So, for instance,
[SPEAKER_20]: have resisted, time and time again, much, much deeper cuts to benefits, to the help given to the most vulnerable, those who fall on hard times, as advocated by Conservatives in government.
[SPEAKER_20]: When people get back into work, particularly those on low pay, I'd be very anxious to make sure they keep more of the money they earn.
[SPEAKER_20]: So when I came into government, you, everybody here, all of us, would start paying income tax the moment you earned £6,400.
[SPEAKER_20]: on the front page of your well-thumbed copy of the 2010 Liberal Democrat manifesto, you would have seen an absolute leading commitment, which we did stick to, which was that we would raise the point at which you pay income tax.
[SPEAKER_20]: So you pay no income tax on the first £10,600 you earn.
[SPEAKER_20]: That has actually meant that 3 million people, over 3 million people, on low pay pay no income tax for the first time ever.
[SPEAKER_20]: The final thing I would say is about the benefit sanctions which you mentioned.
[SPEAKER_20]: I do, I have become persuaded, listening to the Trussell Trust and others who have provided evidence about the reasons people are using food banks, I have become persuaded that we need a, in effect, a kind of a yellow card system, that some of the sanctions that are applied to people who don't meet the conditions of their benefits shouldn't be imposed quite as harshly and automatically as they are, and that is a change that I would want to introduce in the next Parliament.
[SPEAKER_14]: Good evening, Nick.
[SPEAKER_14]: I do think you're an honourable man, but what you're forgetting is that all these sanctions were in place because you put Cameron into number 10.
[SPEAKER_14]: He didn't have a majority, so there'd be no work programme, nowhere near as many benefit sanctions, and you could have made a different choice, and that's why people don't trust you.
[SPEAKER_14]: People like me that voted for you in that election did not vote Liberal Democrat to put Cameron in number 10.
[SPEAKER_14]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_14]: Hang on.
[SPEAKER_14]: What did... Just explain, what did you expect?
[SPEAKER_14]: What did you want?
[SPEAKER_14]: I'm sorry?
[SPEAKER_14]: My preference would have been for him to have continued negotiations with Labour, which I think a lot of Liberal Democrat natural voters are people who voted Labour that were protesting.
[SPEAKER_14]: But can I just make...
[SPEAKER_14]: There's just the little matter of democracy.
[SPEAKER_20]: You could have chosen.
[SPEAKER_20]: You did choose.
[SPEAKER_20]: Accept responsibility.
[SPEAKER_20]: That was your choice.
[SPEAKER_20]: That's not actually the case.
[SPEAKER_20]: After the last election, no one won a majority, whether you all like it or not.
[SPEAKER_20]: The Liberal Democrats did not win.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm not Prime Minister.
[SPEAKER_20]: I lead a party of 8% of MPs in the House of Commons, and it was the Conservatives that won the most votes and seats.
[SPEAKER_14]: great team and now slugging each other off.
[SPEAKER_20]: David Cameron says you were a great team and now you're all slugging each other off.
[SPEAKER_20]: He keeps talking about darkened rooms as does Ed Miliband.
[SPEAKER_20]: I have to say to you if either of them still think they're going to win a majority they need to go and lie down in that darkened room.
[SPEAKER_20]: The point I'd like to make to you and to everybody is this, is that you are the boss, right?
[SPEAKER_20]: We are your servants.
[SPEAKER_20]: You give us, through the way you vote next Thursday, our marching instructions.
[SPEAKER_20]: And last time, the marching instructions were very, very clear.
[SPEAKER_20]: The only way we could create a stable government at a time of an economic firestorm which could have engulfed this country, we could have been the next domino to fall after Greece and Portugal and Spain, was the Conservatives and the Liberal Democrats.
[SPEAKER_14]: Greece our economy and you know it.
[SPEAKER_14]: Our economy was nothing like Greece's and it insults everyone's intelligence to compare the economy of this country to Greece.
[SPEAKER_14]: You're not that stupid.
[SPEAKER_20]: No, I don't.
[SPEAKER_20]: With the greatest respect, please don't be complacent about the state of the British economy.
[SPEAKER_20]: Our banking crisis was considerably worse than Greece's.
[SPEAKER_20]: Our deficit was just as bad.
[SPEAKER_20]: And so were our assets.
[SPEAKER_20]: If you want to see what happens
[SPEAKER_20]: where people don't step up to the plate, however controversial it is, to provide stable government.
[SPEAKER_20]: Look at the 50% youth unemployment in many other European countries where governments haven't got to grips with the economic crisis.
[SPEAKER_20]: I will never apologize, never apologize, whatever the short-term political effects, on the Liberal Democrats for having stepped up to the plate in a very plucky and brave way to put the country before party.
[SPEAKER_18]: I don't know whether the colour of your pullover is... Yellow.
[SPEAKER_18]: It does say something, does it?
[SPEAKER_18]: No.
[SPEAKER_45]: Your question.
[SPEAKER_45]: Good evening, Mr Clegg.
[SPEAKER_45]: You mentioned earlier about democracy.
[SPEAKER_45]: Do I assume from that, that when the phone rings on Friday morning, next Friday morning, that the first person you will speak to will be the person who has most seats?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yeah, I think the party that gets the biggest mandate from you, in other words the party with the most votes and the most seats, even if they haven't got a slam-dunk result, has in a democracy the result, the right, forgive me, to make, if you like the first move, to reach out to other parties to assemble a government if they so choose.
[SPEAKER_20]: It may not then work out.
[SPEAKER_20]: other parties may not reciprocate, and then other arrangements might need to be arrived at.
[SPEAKER_20]: But I think in a democracy it just seems to me a pretty old-fashioned principle that the party that has got its nose ahead of the other parties because of the way you vote, even if they haven't got an outright majority, has got the mandate to try and put together a government.
[SPEAKER_18]: All right.
[SPEAKER_18]: Before we go on to another question, does anybody else want to speak about food banks specifically, which was the question we had?
[SPEAKER_18]: And take a point, no?
[SPEAKER_18]: All right, let's go on to a question from Grace Davis, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: Grace Davis.
[SPEAKER_22]: Is free movement within the UK creating a problem in the EU?
[SPEAKER_22]: Creating a problem in the UK?
[SPEAKER_18]: Free movement within the EU, is it creating a problem in the UK?
[SPEAKER_20]: I think it did create a problem when free movement became kind of the same as the freedom to claim.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't think the freedom to move is the same as the freedom to claim.
[SPEAKER_20]: And so, even though I am pro-European, not because I think it's perfect, but I think it makes sense for an open economy to be part of the world's largest marketplace, even though I am pro-European, I decided as Deputy Prime Minister in this coalition government to break that link so that people couldn't arrive here from elsewhere in the European Union and claim benefits, no questions asked, on the first day they arrive.
[SPEAKER_20]: I, by the way, would also point out it is a two-way street.
[SPEAKER_20]: There are roughly about as many Brits
[SPEAKER_20]: living and working elsewhere in the European Union than there are Europeans working in our country.
[SPEAKER_20]: So we kind of got to remember that it's also a freedom which many, many, many of us British people also benefit from elsewhere in Europe.
[SPEAKER_18]: Where do you stand on the question of a referendum?
[SPEAKER_18]: Because we had
[SPEAKER_18]: We had David Cameron saying there was no way that he'd do any kind of deal which didn't allow a referendum on Europe after the negotiations.
[SPEAKER_20]: So David Cameron and I, together actually in coalition government, legislated for the circumstances in which a referendum will take place.
[SPEAKER_20]: So you're happy with that?
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, I'll come to, I am happy with that.
[SPEAKER_20]: He appears to have changed his mind.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think it is perfectly sensible to say to you, in law, that in future if your powers, if the
[SPEAKER_20]: The sovereignty of our nation is in any way shared or pooled with the European Union.
[SPEAKER_20]: At that point it should be your choice whether we carry on in the European Union or not.
[SPEAKER_20]: It shouldn't be the choice of the Parliament or the government of the day.
[SPEAKER_20]: We shouldn't be able to instead give your powers away behind your back.
[SPEAKER_20]: That is what we legislated for in 2011 and there are stirring speeches by William Hague and David Cameron in the House of Commons saying this is the right approach.
[SPEAKER_20]: Within months
[SPEAKER_20]: The ink was barely dry on the legislation.
[SPEAKER_20]: The Conservatives have now changed their mind again, and again, and again, and again.
[SPEAKER_20]: But I remain of the view, as I always have done, is that we should have a referendum on whether we should stay in or leave the European Union when new powers are given up to the European Union.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I will, by the way, again, shock horror, always argue that we remain part of the European Union, flawed though it is, because I think if we quit, we become poorer, unemployment goes up, and investment in our country goes down.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_18]: The logic of what you say, in view of what David Cameron said earlier in this programme, is that you can't go into coalition with him because you will only allow a referendum if powers are given to the European Union.
[SPEAKER_18]: He wants to repatriate some powers and then have a referendum and says he won't be Prime Minister if he can't.
[SPEAKER_20]: So he might as well say goodbye, goodbye to the coalition.
[SPEAKER_20]: You should have taken the opportunity when David Cameron was here to ask him about the Conservative position on Europe.
[SPEAKER_20]: I can only tell you about...
[SPEAKER_18]: He did explain it.
[SPEAKER_18]: No, you've probably heard it.
[SPEAKER_20]: The Conservatives now say they want to renegotiate but they won't tell you how they'll renegotiate.
[SPEAKER_20]: They float different dates about when they want to have a referendum.
[SPEAKER_20]: 2017?
[SPEAKER_20]: No, sometimes they say 2016, sometimes they say they're going to leave the European Union if they don't get what they want, sometimes they say they'll stay.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't know what they're going to think on Europe next Tuesday, let alone on May the 8th.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think there should be a referendum, I say this as a pro-European, whether we stay in or when we go out, where new powers are given up by us as a country
[SPEAKER_20]: to the European Union in the future.
[SPEAKER_18]: Only when new powers are given up.
[SPEAKER_18]: The man up there with spectacles, I think you've spoken already, but anyway, there we go.
[SPEAKER_18]: And then I'll come to you up there at the very back, under the big organ pipe.
[SPEAKER_31]: Yes, sir.
[SPEAKER_31]: We've got eight countries that are about to possibly leave the European Union, and we've got still the Eurozone crisis lying underneath.
[SPEAKER_31]: Eight countries about to leave?
[SPEAKER_31]: Yeah, we've got Spain, we've got Cyprus.
[SPEAKER_31]: They're in danger of leaving.
[SPEAKER_31]: There's a chance that they will leave soon.
[SPEAKER_31]: We've got the eurozone debt crisis still underneath the surface, and we've got 30% government bonds, European government bonds, trading at negative interest rates.
[SPEAKER_31]: And Germany, the heart of the EU, 70% of its government bonds are trading at negative interest rates.
[SPEAKER_31]: I want to know how bad does it have to get before you would think, perhaps now we should leave?
[SPEAKER_20]: Look, I don't, by the way, think eight countries will leave.
[SPEAKER_20]: It's a possibility.
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, everything is a possibility.
[SPEAKER_20]: But I absolutely don't think it's going to happen.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'll tell you why.
[SPEAKER_20]: Because in a globalized world,
[SPEAKER_20]: where we have big borderless threats like climate change, human traffickers and crime which cross borders.
[SPEAKER_20]: We have these massive corporations that sort of go from one continent to the other.
[SPEAKER_20]: You've got capital flows going from one corner of the planet to the next.
[SPEAKER_20]: It makes sense.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think we become stronger when we do things together.
[SPEAKER_20]: I just think we can fight crime, we can fight climate change, we can regulate big global corporations better when we do it together.
[SPEAKER_20]: By the way, it's a very similar argument to why I so passionately believe in the country, the United Kingdom, that I love so much and I don't want to see it pulled apart.
[SPEAKER_20]: Because I think we are just, quite simply, stronger when we do things together rather than when we fall apart.
[SPEAKER_31]: But it still isn't an answer to my question, which was how bad would it have to get?
[SPEAKER_31]: For example,
[SPEAKER_31]: If Greece was to leave the European Union, and then if France, which looks set to possibly vote in...
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't...
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm sorry, can I interrupt?
[SPEAKER_31]: France could possibly vote in the Eurosceptic National Front, and if they do, they would pull out.
[SPEAKER_18]: Then more and more countries... Let's not have the whole description.
[SPEAKER_18]: How bad does it have to get?
[SPEAKER_18]: Is there other circumstances in which you would say Britain
[SPEAKER_20]: and should be.
[SPEAKER_20]: Big legal firms, big aerospace firms would invest in our country if we were sort of bobbing along somewhere in the mid-Atlantic, friendless, unable to sell into our own European neighbourhood.
[SPEAKER_20]: Of course not.
[SPEAKER_20]: Jobs are at stake.
[SPEAKER_18]: We would still be able to sell to Europe.
[SPEAKER_18]: Alright, we've heard your point.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_18]: Sorry not to keep with you, but I want to go to the man up there.
[SPEAKER_18]: If you believe in true democracy like you've mentioned a few times, you give the British people the say on the European Union.
[SPEAKER_20]: So I've explained the reasons not only when a referendum will take place, but more than that, I'm the first Deputy Prime Minister, we're the first government to ever put that into law.
[SPEAKER_18]: Alright, let's go on to another question.
[SPEAKER_18]: Brenda Hammonds, please.
[SPEAKER_18]: We haven't got much time left.
[SPEAKER_18]: Brenda Hammonds.
[SPEAKER_01]: With rising tension in Russia and the Middle East, will you support the need for the Trident nuclear deterrent?
[SPEAKER_20]: Where do you stand on the Trident nuclear deterrent?
[SPEAKER_20]: So I think we should keep the nuclear deterrent in this unsafe world, but I don't think we need to keep it on the same basis on which it was originally designed to flatten Moscow at the press of a button.
[SPEAKER_20]: and this comes down to basically whether the Trident nuclear system has four nuclear submarines or three nuclear submarines and whether you need a nuclear submarine absolutely 24 hours a day, 365 days of the whole year going around the world.
[SPEAKER_20]: I personally think we can step down the nuclear ladder
[SPEAKER_20]: while keeping ourselves safe.
[SPEAKER_20]: And that, I think, is a sensible, balanced way to keep ourselves safe, but not spend huge amounts of money on a Cold War replacement to the nuclear trident system, which just doesn't fit the post-Cold War world that we live in.
[SPEAKER_20]: The kind of threats we face, by the way, aren't like the Cold War.
[SPEAKER_20]: They are now stateless groups, extremist groups, terrorist groups.
[SPEAKER_20]: The civil war that we're seeing raging in Syria and elsewhere, those are the big threats.
[SPEAKER_20]: They're not solved by having four nuclear submarines rather than three.
[SPEAKER_20]: You sit up there at the back.
[SPEAKER_18]: You've spoken already, but have another go.
[SPEAKER_09]: You talk about keeping the country safe.
[SPEAKER_09]: When was this country last time attacked by another country?
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, we are under threat from people who don't want to attack in the conventional sense, but want to attack us, maim fellow citizens.
[SPEAKER_20]: It's because we're meddling in their countries.
[SPEAKER_20]: Can I... Well, I don't actually think there's any excuse that any rational or reasonable person can give to those people who want to kill innocent British citizens through terrorist acts in our cities.
[SPEAKER_20]: And whilst... Whilst...
[SPEAKER_20]: Whilst as a good old-fashioned liberal, I'm the first person to defend our civil liberties and our freedoms, I think there is no inconsistency between defending our freedoms and keeping ourselves safe.
[SPEAKER_20]: We don't make ourselves any less free by making ourselves any less safe.
[SPEAKER_18]: One last thing, if I could ask you this.
[SPEAKER_18]: You've said you want the Liberal Democrats to be the heart for the Conservatives, the brains for Labour.
[SPEAKER_18]: If neither of those works and you can't form a coalition, would you remain leader of the Liberal Democrats?
[SPEAKER_18]: or would you see your job as over?
[SPEAKER_20]: Look, I want to carry on.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm 48 years old.
[SPEAKER_20]: I've got bags of energy.
[SPEAKER_20]: I believe in what the Liberal Democrats stand for, which is to strike the right balance between creating a strong economy but doing so fairly.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't think that's represented on either the right or the left of British politics.
[SPEAKER_20]: But look, no, I have to stop you there.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you very much indeed.
[SPEAKER_18]: A nice, brief answer.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_18]: Sorry to cut Mr. Clake short, but we do have to stop because we have exactly 90 minutes for this program.
[SPEAKER_18]: That ends, incidentally, of course, as you would guess, this edition of Question Time.
[SPEAKER_18]: We're going to be back, not next Thursday when we have the election results, but on Friday evening at 9 o'clock when we'll be looking back at the election and seeing what's happened, a first chance to talk about it.
[SPEAKER_18]: So from here, my thanks, of course, to our party leaders and particularly to all of you who came to take part in it in Leeds.
[SPEAKER_18]: Good night.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, we've covered him next on BBC1.
[SPEAKER_04]: And what exactly has Kayleigh been doing with Ken, her 80-year-old labour?
[SPEAKER_04]: John can't believe it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's Peter Kay's Car Share.